<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The faithfull depositaty [sic] of sound doctrine and ancient truths maintained against all oppositions of science, falsely so called, and against the prophane and vaine bablings of unsound teachers, or, A treatise on the I Tim. 6. 20 / by R.J., D.D. ; with the authors farewell to his hearers, readers, if not to the world.</title>
            <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25240</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27158839</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205727</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264176440</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J562A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">27158839</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25240)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1722:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The faithfull depositaty [sic] of sound doctrine and ancient truths maintained against all oppositions of science, falsely so called, and against the prophane and vaine bablings of unsound teachers, or, A treatise on the I Tim. 6. 20 / by R.J., D.D. ; with the authors farewell to his hearers, readers, if not to the world.</title>
                  <author>Jenison, Robert, 1584?-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S.B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Newcastle :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, stained, print show-through, and loss of test.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="uniform_title">Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 1st, VI, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205727:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:205727:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Faithfull</hi> DEPOSITATY OF SOVND DOCTRINE AND ANCIENT TRVTHS: Maintained against all Oppositions of Science, <hi>falsely so called;</hi> and against the prophane and Vaine Bablings of unsound Teachers.</p>
            <p>OR, <hi>A Treatise on the</hi> 1 Tim, 6, 20. By <hi>R. J.</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the Authors Farewell to his Hearers. Readers, if not, to the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Newcastle,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. B.</hi> 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:205727:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:205727:2"/>
            <head>To the Reverend his Brethren, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured Friends of the CLASSIS of the Town and County of <hi>New-Castle</hi> upon <hi>Tine.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THese Sermon Notes, Preached by your Appointment and Entreaty at two severall Ordination, and which <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Of M.</hi> Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Hender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, <hi>Aprial</hi> 13. 1640. <hi>And of Mr.</hi> Iohn Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> since, partly through the importunity of some of you particularly, at severall times (which yet took little Impression then) and chiesly upon the earnest motion since, of the whole Classis Assembled, were length (though not promised to you then yet afterwards, whilest I looked on Gods Call by you) made ready for the Publick View; I now present unto you.</p>
            <p>You have made them <hi>your own</hi> by your care nest solicitation and request. <hi>Mine</hi> they are, and I <hi>own</hi> them for matter of pains, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever weaknesse and defects may espied in them. <hi>Gods they are</hi> for his assistance, and for whatsoever is good, true, and wholesome in
<pb facs="tcp:205727:3"/> them. <hi>The Churches they are</hi> for use, benefit and Instruction; for whose good, next to Gods glory (seeing you have judged them fit to be Published for those ends). I have now made them yours, to be disposed of by you. If now, upon further perusall, your <hi>Eye</hi> shall second and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the former judgement of your <hi>Eare,</hi> you may have liberty (for me) to make them the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of other Mens Eyes, as well as your own. But then if others look not on them with a like bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent Eye and aspect, you must also look to beare a like share with me in such censures as the curious, if not scornfull Eye of some shall cast upon them. However, I shall entreat the Father of Mercies, to give unto his Church and People, in these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided and unbrideled Times (being otherwise hopefull for Reformation and true Liberty) <hi>the Spirit of Power, of Love, and of a sound mind and judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So I rest and remaine still the same in this mine. Old Age, that is, The Lord Christs, yours, and the Churches Servant. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aged.</hi> 67.</note>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. Jenison.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205727:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 Tim. 6. 20.</bibl>
               <q>O <hi>Timothy,</hi> keep that which is committed to thy Trust, avoyding Prophane and Vaine bablings, and oppositions of Science, falsely so called.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hese Words are part of <hi>Pauls</hi> Charge given to <note place="margin">Pauls <hi>Charge to</hi> Timothy.</note>
               <hi>Timothy,</hi> and in him to all faithfull Ministers of the Gospel, for the use of the whole Church to the end of the World. <hi>Paul</hi> having Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Church at <hi>Ephesus,</hi> left <hi>Timothy</hi> there to make an end of Ordering and Establishing the same. And because the Devill had already sown many false Doctrines and nice questions (by the means especially of false Christianized Jews) who corrupted the Purity of the Gospel in that Church, <hi>Paul</hi> (elsewhere imployed in Planting Churches) Writes this Epistle to him, <hi>to instruct, strengthen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 14. 15.</note>
               <hi>and encourage him;</hi> Exhorting him to Root out that evill Seed of false Doctrine, and to maintain the <hi>truth</hi> in its Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the Church in its Integrity: foretelling also of other horrible abuses and corruptions which would befall the Church in insuing Ages; exhorting him to forewarn the Church thereof, that it might beware of such things. Now besides di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Lessons taught, and admonitions given; he especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note place="margin">Especially c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himselfe and other Ministers to be Ordained.</note> gives Precepts necessary for <hi>Pastors,</hi> that they not onely preserve a good Forme in the state of the Church (both for Doctrine &amp; discipline) in their times; but may leave the Church well established therein, in after times. And himself having had the <hi>glorious Gospel of the blessed God committed to his trust,</hi> by Christ <hi>who inabled him, and counted him faithfull, putting him into the Ministery,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 11. 12. Gal. 2. 7. and having committed the same to <hi>Timothy</hi> in a <hi>summe and forme of sound</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:205727:4"/>
               <hi>Words;</hi> he not onely chargeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to <hi>hold fast that forme himself,</hi> and to <hi>keep that good thing which was committed unto him,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. 14. and here 1 Tim. 6. 20. but he would have him charge others, that they Teach no other Doctrine, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. and <hi>partieularly,</hi> not Doctrines of Liberty, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 1. 2. 3. 4. neither <hi>give heed to Fables,</hi> 1 Tim. 14. and that <hi>they strive not about words, to no profit, but to the subverting of the hearers,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Tim. 2. 14. But as for him (and other true Pastors) he would have him <hi>to warre a good warfare, holdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g Faith and a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18. 19. <hi>and to exercise himselfe</hi> (rather) <hi>unto godlinesse,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 7. But now <hi>Paul</hi> having given <hi>Timothy</hi> this especiall Charge concerning such as he was to <hi>Ordain</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point</hi> to the Ministery, <hi>to lay hands suddenly on no Man,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 22. (And indeed men are not to be installed into Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Office rashly or suddenly, without sufficient examination of <hi>gifts,</hi> and triall of life and conversation:) these particulars <note place="margin">In six particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars.</note> following are given in charge by him to <hi>Timothy,</hi> for himself and those others on whom he was to lay on hands, (and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <note place="margin">As concerning <hi>August</hi> 29. 1648. <hi>pag.</hi> 23. 6.</note> to which, its thought fit that demands be made to such, as by the Forme of our Church Government, are to be Ordained Ministers.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Paul</hi> would have <hi>Timothy</hi> (and all such) <hi>to have a right Faith in Christ,</hi> and a firme perswasion of the truth, or <hi>Faith</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Their faith and soundnesse in it.</note>
               <hi>of God,</hi> which he is to Preach. <hi>This</hi> Charge <hi>I commit unto thee Sonne</hi> Timothy<hi>—holding Faith,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18. 19. that is, the true Doctrine of Faith, thy selfe; and <hi>charging others that they Teach no other Doctrine</hi> ver. 3. <hi>neither give heed to Fables, &amp;c.</hi> ver. 4. 5. even as <hi>Paul</hi> himself was <hi>Ordained a Preacher, and an Apostle, a Teacher of the Gentiles in Faith and Verity,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 7. such must <hi>hold the faithfull Word, as they have been taught,</hi> Tit. 1. 9. <hi>and speak things which become sound Doctrine,</hi> Tit. 2. 1. <hi>other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise,</hi> nothing but <hi>Pride</hi> will follow in <hi>Novices,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 6. and through Pride, <hi>contentions, envy, strife, railings, evill surmisings, perverse disputings of men of corrupt minds, or gulling one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (as now, especially in these our dayes we find, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 4. 5. He would not have us <hi>consent to any that teach otherwise,</hi>
               <note place="margin">And perswasion of the truth they teach.</note> and who themselves <hi>consent not to whole somewords,</hi> ver. 3. <hi>or to the Doctrine which is according to godlinesse,</hi> he would have us perswaded of the truth which we professe, against all opposite errours of the times.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:205727:4"/> 2. <hi>Paul</hi> would have such as enter the Ministery, in desiring that Office, to <hi>intend</hi> the <hi>work</hi> of it, and not the honour sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; <note place="margin">2. Concerning their <hi>Ends</hi> and <hi>Aymes</hi> in desiring the <hi>Ministery.</hi>
               </note> yea, and to doe <hi>good</hi> in it, it being a <hi>good worke,</hi> and not (so much) to receive honour from it; nor would he have such <hi>either</hi> to ayme at any other base end, as <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> as some for that end <hi>teach things they ought not,</hi> Tit. 1. 11. <hi>or</hi> to doe ought of that nature, no not Preach Christ, out of the grounds of envie and strife, and of contention, to adde affliction to other godly Ministers, as <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. 15. 16. he would have <hi>us rightly to divide the Word of truth,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 15. <hi>and for such as are zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of spirituall gifts, he would have them follow after Charioy, and desire Spirituall gifts, but rather that they may Prophesie, and that they would seek</hi> (not to vaunt themselves in speaking in <hi>unknown or strange Tongues,</hi> and in a vain ostentation of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing▪ falfely so called or with <hi>excellency of Speech,</hi> or of <hi>(humano) Wisedom, and the entising words thereof,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 1. 4. but) <hi>that they may excell to the edifying of the Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 1. 2. 4. 5. 12.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He would have such as <hi>are in,</hi> or enter into the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to be men of <hi>resolution,</hi> that they will use constant dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence <note place="margin">3. Their Resolution and diligence in it.</note> in all the duties thereof, <hi>to give attendance to Reading,</hi> (not to depend on Revelations) <hi>to Exhortation, and to Doctrine; and to Meditate on these things, and to give themselves wholly to them,</hi> 1 Tim 4. 13. 15. and accordingly to <hi>stir up the gift of God, which is in them,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 6. and <hi>to be strong in the grace that is in Christ Jesus,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 1. and in Preaching, to be <hi>instant in season, and out of season; to reprove, rebuke, with all long suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and doctrine,</hi> for which he gives <hi>Timothy</hi> (and in him; all other faithfull Ministers) a very deep charge, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. 2. <hi>and</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 21. <hi>and</hi> 6. 13. 14.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He would have such to be <hi>Zealous and Faithfull</hi> in keeping and maintaining the truth of the Gospel committed to them, <note place="margin">4. Their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and Zeale in maintaining the truth.</note> and the purity of the Church against errour and Schisme, &amp;c. even as he himself <hi>by Jesus Christ was counted faithfull, and by him put into the Ministery,</hi> 1 Tim 1. 11. he would have them <hi>to teach no other Doctrine, neither to give heed to Fables, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 3. 4. <hi>but to hold fast the Forme of sound words, which he had taught in faith and love,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. <hi>and to keep that good thing which is committed to them,</hi> ver. 14. and as in the Text, <hi>Keep that which is committed to thy trust; avoyding, &amp;c.</hi> of which more anone.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205727:5"/> 5. <hi>Paul</hi> would have such to be also <hi>unblameable for life and conversation,</hi> and to be <hi>examples of beleevers in word, conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 5.Their unblame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life.</note>
               <hi>and charity,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 12. and ver. 16. <hi>to take heed to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi> (as well as to Doctrine) and <hi>to hold</hi> (as Faith, so) <hi>a good Conscience,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 19. And in particular for the qualities and vertues required in Bishops or Overseers, and other Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall Persons; see at large, 1 Tim. 3, 2. 3. They must be <hi>blamelesse, &amp;c.</hi> and among other things <hi>of good</hi> (and modest) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, given to hospitality, apt to teach, not given to Wine, no strikers,</hi> not greedy of <hi>filthy lucre,</hi> not <hi>covetous, &amp;c.</hi> And therefore speaking of such perverse Disputers as suppose <hi>gain is godlinesse,</hi> and of the <hi>love of money, and coveting after it</hi> (as a cause of erring, or being seduced from the Faith) he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently adds, <hi>but thou ô man of God, flee these things, and follow after Righteousnesse, Godlinesse, Faith, Love, Patience, Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 5. 10. 11. And writing to <hi>Titus,</hi> he thus di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects him (and others) both for life and doctrine, <hi>In all things shew thy selfe a Pattern of good works; In Doctrine shewing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptnesse, gravity, sincerity, sound speech, &amp;c.</hi> Tit. 2. 7. 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And lastly, he requires in such, <hi>a purpose to continue in their duty against all trouble and persecution, and not to be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. Constancy and purpose to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
               <hi>of the testimony of our Lord, but to be partaker of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of the Gospel, according to the power of God,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 8. <hi>and to endure hardnesse,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 3. <hi>and afflictions,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 5. <hi>and that by his own example,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 10. 11. with 14. <hi>and</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 12. <hi>and</hi> Acts 20. 23. 24.</p>
            <p>But now to pitch especially upon the fourth of these.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Charge,</hi> in the Words of my Text, given unto <hi>Timothy</hi>
               <note place="margin">The speciall <hi>Charge</hi> here gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to <hi>Timothy.</hi>
               </note> is of speciall weight, and as it were the summe and whole of all with which he concludes this his first Epistle, breaking off all the rest, as if all were nothing to this; exciting hereunto by name, using at once an Appellation <hi>Timothy;</hi> and an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, <hi>O Timothy, Keep that which is committed to thy trust,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ten paracatatheken phúlaxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that in these Words, we have first, A speciall <hi>Charge</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Parts. 1. A Charge. 2. A Direction how to keep it.</note> given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> the first Bishop or Overseer of the Church of the <hi>Ephesians.</hi> Secondly, A <hi>Direction</hi> to the way, means, and manner of keeping it, in the Words, <hi>Avoyding prophane and vain bablings, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205727:5"/> 1. The Charge is to keep this <hi>Depositum,</hi> or <hi>that which is committed to his trust.</hi> Concerning which, we have these <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. The Charge is</hi> to keep that vvhich is committed to his trust. VVhere, foure things.</note> foure things to consider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Who</hi> gives this Charge.</item>
               <item>2. To <hi>whom</hi> it is given.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>What</hi> this <hi>Depositum,</hi> or thing committed to his charge is.</item>
               <item>4. The <hi>Charge it selfe,</hi> or <hi>Duty of keeping it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Who</hi> gives it? <hi>Paul,</hi> This <hi>Charge I commit unto thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Who</hi> gives this <hi>Charge.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Sonne</hi> Timothy, <hi>according to the Prophesies which went before on thee, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18. <hi>Paul</hi> who had been charged with the <note place="margin">1 Paul, <hi>Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rially.</hi>
               </note> Gospel himself, as is said, gives this charge in the name of God, to <hi>Timothy,</hi> not onely in this Epistle, but also (in his old Age) in the last Epistle that ever he Writ, his second to <hi>Timothy,</hi> which he writ in Prison at <hi>Rome,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. 14. <hi>Held fast the Forme of sound Words, which thou hast heard of me, in Faith and Love which is in Christ Jesus:</hi> That <hi>good thing which was committed to thee, keep, by the Holy Ghost which dwelleth in us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This example of his lets us see <hi>how carefull, faithfull Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters</hi>
               <note place="margin">VVhich teacheth to transmit sound Doctrine to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steritie, by the example of <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>are, and should be, of the good estate of the Church, and of soundnesse of Doctrine, when they are gone, transmitting the forme of wholesome Words and Doctrine of the Church unto Posterity;</hi> To which end <hi>Timothy</hi> is further charged in these Words. 2 Tim. 2. 2. <hi>And the things which thou hast heard of me, among many witnesses, the same commit thou to faithfull men, who shall be able to teach others also.</hi> The like charge, in effect, <hi>Paul</hi> gives to the Elders of that Church of the <hi>Ephesians</hi> (who were to see his Face no more) telling them both what should befall to himself, and to them also; and how that after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, <hi>grievous Wolves should enter in among them, not spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Flock: Also of their own selves should men arise, speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perverse things, to draw away disciples after them; and therefore, he commits</hi> Gods Flock to them, in these Words, Take <hi>heed therefore unto your selves, and to all the Flock over the which the Holy Ghost hath made you Overseers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchased with his own blood,</hi> Acts 20. 17. 18.—25.—28. 29.</p>
            <p>The like Charge he leaves with <hi>Titus.</hi> See <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 5. 6. 9. 10. 11. 14. <hi>and Chap.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>But speak thou the things which</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205727:6"/>
               <hi>become sound Doctrine, &amp;c.</hi> To this example of <hi>Paul,</hi> I will onely add that of <hi>Peter</hi> (to whom the Gospel (especially) <note place="margin">And of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </note> of the Circumcision was committed, as the Gospel of the uncircumcision was to <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 2. 7.) he knowing his death was at hand, is carefull to remember them of their duty, that by Faith and good works they would make their Calling fure, and to warn them to be constant in the Faith of Christ, which he doth (not by Preaching and telling them of any new truths or lights, but) by putting them in remembrance of such things as they did already know, being (in seeming at least) established in the present truth: <hi>I will endeavour,</hi> saith he, <hi>that you may be able after my decease, to have these things</hi> (these ancient, present, and fundamentall truths) <hi>alwayes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 12. 13. 14. 15. See also, 2 Pet. 2, 1. 2. 3. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And if we, especially in these dayes when so many false Teachers add Heresies are abroad uncontrouled, doe our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, both by Preaching and Writing, as God enables, to vindicate the truth, and to transmit it pure and sound unto Posterity, we doe but our duty, and, in all good Conscience, seek to discharge the trust committed to us, and commended both by the Precept and Practise of the holy Apostles, <hi>Paul, Peter,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>But what? Had <hi>Timothy</hi> here his Charge onely from <hi>Paul?</hi> No, we heard that <hi>Paul</hi> committed this Charge to him, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od and Christ authoritatively.</note>
               <hi>to the Prophesies which went before on him,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18, And these were from God. And accordingly, <hi>Paul</hi> chargeth <hi>Timothy</hi> before God, and the <hi>Lord Jesus Christ, who shall judge the quick and the dead, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 21. and 2 Tim. 4. 1. 2. that is, in the name, and as in the presence of God and Christ, by their command, and as he will answer it to them, when he was to give his accounts. So that it is God and Christ that calls and Ordains Ministers <hi>authoritatively;</hi> and <hi>Paul, Timothy,</hi> and their Successors, <hi>Ministerially,</hi> and by a Power derived. The call is chiefly and originally from God, who inables and puts into the Ministery, but he doth this by the hand ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and Ministery of men, his Officers, and by the means of an <hi>externall call and Commission.</hi> As again, 1 Tim. 4. 14. <hi>Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect not the gift that is in thee, which was given thee by Prophesie</hi> (and therefore from God) <hi>with the laying on of the</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:205727:6"/>
               <hi>hands of the Presbytery,</hi> and 2 Tim. 1. 6. <hi>Stir up the gift of God which is in thee, by the putting on of my hands,</hi> saith <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where we see both calls▪ (both from God and Man) do and <note place="margin">Both calls (from God and Man) must usually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre.</note> must concurre, and the Call, Commission and Command to Preach (as a Pubiique Officer) is not onely from God, but from the Church, and from the one (in an ordinary way at least, which by <hi>Paul</hi> here and other <hi>Apostles</hi> was settled in all Churches, for all Ages) as well as from the other. Of which a touch hereafter again.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now secondly, To <hi>whom</hi> is this Charge given? I answer, Its given by name to <hi>Timothy;</hi> and by way of <hi>Exclamation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.To whom this Charge is given, To</hi> Timothy. Vincent. Leri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens.</note>
               <hi>O</hi> Timothy: This ô, or exclamation, saith one, <hi>Exclamatio ista &amp; praescientiae est pariter, &amp; charitatis,</hi> argued in him both foresight of errours, and Love or Charity; <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>videbat enim futuros, quos etiam praedolebat errores,</hi> for he foresaw those er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours would be, which he could not but grieve to foresee.</p>
            <p>But <hi>what?</hi> Is this Charge given to him onely? No, <hi>Quis est</hi>
               <note place="margin">And to all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters especially.</note>
               <hi>hodiè</hi> Timotheus? <hi>nisi vel universa Ecclesia, vel specialiter to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum corpus praepositorum?</hi> Who is <hi>Timothy</hi> in these our dayes. but either the Whole, or Universall Church, or specially the whole Body of the Rulers and Elders in it? who should both know, and teach the whole, and the onely will and worship of God, and hold fast the forme of sound words, received from the Apostles, &amp;c. We all, both Ministers and People must look to meet with such errours, and to arme against them, by holding to ancient truths, and to the Scriptures of God, as <hi>Peter</hi> directs us, 2 <hi>Pet. ch.</hi> 1. 19. 20. with <hi>ch.</hi> 2. 1. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>What</hi> then is it, <hi>which is to be kept?</hi> or <hi>what</hi> is <hi>this thing</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. What this Charg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or matter of Trust is.</note>
               <hi>which is committed to his trust?</hi> I shall give answer hereunto, 1. <hi>Negatively.</hi> 2. <hi>Affirmatively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Negatively,</hi> Those of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Bedarmine</hi> by name, will tell us that hereby are meant <hi>Traditions.</hi>
               <note place="margin">I. Negatively. <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Traditions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the Written VVord.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Well; I will onely thus <hi>reason:</hi> That which <hi>Paul</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the trust of <hi>Timothy,</hi> is no other then the forme of words which <hi>Timothy</hi> heard of him, and was to hold fast and keep, 2. Tim 1. 13. 14. Now this was either agreeable to the Scriptures, or not. If agreeable, then Papists gain nothing for such their Traditions as they pleade for. What advantage <note place="margin">A strong Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment against Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Traditions.</note> is it to them, or disadvantage to us, that <hi>Paul</hi> first Preached
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205727:7"/> and delivered in a summe and forme of wholesome words, what he after wrote, (or, which is not so likely, that he first wrote, what he after Preached?) But if not agreeable, then must he be accursed by his own Verdict, (as he and we are by theirs,) <hi>Galat.</hi> 1. 8, <hi>Though we,</hi> saith he, <hi>or an Angel from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Preach any other Gospel then that which we have Preached unto you, let him he accursed;</hi> Where it being in the Originall onely (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or) <hi>besides that which we have Preached,</hi> condemns not onely such as teach <hi>contrary,</hi> but <hi>praeter▪ besides</hi> Scripture, (which two yet, in matters of Faith are in effect, all one) and <hi>Paul</hi> speaks not onely against such as did bring in a New Gospel, but against such as inverted, or perverted that which he taught. The words which <hi>Paul</hi> taught <hi>Timothy</hi> were <hi>whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Words</hi> (sound in themselves, and healing words) <hi>even the Words of our Lord Jesus Christ, the Doctrine which is according to godlinesse:</hi> and if he himself did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> teach other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then, by his own sentence, he was <hi>Proud, knowing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> as in this Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. 4.</p>
            <p>What he taught then, was (at least) Apostolicall, and therefore <hi>Divine,</hi> for it skils not whether God and Christ spake <hi>viva</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVhat</hi> Paul <hi>gave in charge he both found written, and left written.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Voce,</hi> immediately, or by such his Messengers, as whom he In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spired with the Holy Ghost, first to speak, and then to Write what they taught.</p>
            <p>God reveals his <hi>whole will</hi> to his <hi>Sonne Christ;</hi> he to the holy <hi>Ghost</hi> (which receives of his) and so by it to the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> and other Pen-men of holy Writ; they to us, by <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi> which Writing, or Word Written, is left to the Church, as the rule of Faith and manners, to the end of the World, (whatsoever some, whether older and Popish, or new and Fanatick Masters would tell us.) Yea, what <hi>Paul</hi> delivered was the Written word of God, which he both found Written, and left Written, as did also the other Apostles and men of God. <hi>Paul was separated unto the Gospel of God, which he had promised afore by his Prophets in the holy Scriptures</hi> Rom. 1. 1. 2. <note place="margin">That was the whole Counsell of God.</note> neither Preached he to any any other Gospel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 26. He Preached, <hi>(ouden ectos) no other things then those which the Prophets and</hi> Moses <hi>did say should come,</hi> Acts 26. 22. But where said they them? Where are these things to be found but in holy Scripture? <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 25. with 27. where <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:205727:7"/> reduceth all which <hi>Moses</hi> and the <hi>Prophets</hi> spake, to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Thus <hi>Paul</hi> ever proved his Doctrine by <hi>Scripture, Acts</hi> 17. 2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 3.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Paul,</hi> having according to the Scripture, delivered the <hi>whole counsell of God,</hi> Acts 20. 27. (and that to this Church of the <hi>Ephesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns)</hi> it followeth, that either Gods whole will was not revealed to him, or that he taught nothing (at least for substance) which was not formerly Written by <hi>Moses</hi> and the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Yea, as he and others found the summe of Heavenly Doctrine Written; so he and they left it (and no other) Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <note place="margin">So did other Apostles also.</note> though more fully and plainly. This is expressely and generally avouched by Saint <hi>John,</hi> 1 John 1. 1. 2. 3. 4. <hi>That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes—declare we unto you,</hi> (that is by Preaching) <hi>And these things,</hi> (these same and no other things) <hi>we Write unto you, that your joy may be full.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Christ had first said to him, and to the rest, I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you Friends; <hi>For all things that I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you.</hi> And did he not the like to <hi>Paul</hi> think ye, who had his Call from Jesus Christ, and received, and was taught the Gospel, <hi>Not by Man, but by the revelation of</hi> Jesus Christ, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 11. 12. to whom the whole counsell of God was made known? now, saith <hi>John,</hi> for himselfe and others, <hi>And these</hi> (same) <hi>things Write we unto you.</hi> What they as Christs <hi>Disciples</hi> received from Christ, that as <hi>Preachers</hi> and Publishers of his will, they taught by word of mouth, and delivered to others, as <hi>Paul</hi> here, to <hi>Timothy;</hi> and as his <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries</hi> and Scribes they wrote the same (even as they found it more briefly written) to the Churches of God, and to us.</p>
            <p>So that we may conclude hence, the <hi>unnecessarinesse,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of Popish Traditions, whereby (though they pretend <note place="margin">The unnecessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinesse.</note> and call them Apostolicall, yet) they doe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> teach other Doctrine, so charging the Scripture with Imperfection, <note place="margin">1. Of Popish Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> contrary to the Doctrine of the Scripture, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. 29. <hi>John</hi> 20. 31. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Of supposed <hi>New Lights,</hi> and Revelations of the Spirit, without or against the Word, upon pretence whereof the suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Of supposed</hi> New-Lights.</note> yea and authority of the Sriptures is denied or lessened.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:205727:8"/> 2. I answer <hi>affirmatively,</hi> that by the thing here committed to the trust of <hi>Timothy,</hi> are ment these foure things. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Affirmatively.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y this matter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rust are meant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oure things.</note>
            </p>
            <p>1. <hi>The Doctrine of the Scriptures.</hi> 2. <hi>Ministeriall Gifts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. <hi>The Office of Preaching.</hi> 4. And lastly, <hi>The care of Soules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>first thing</hi> then which is ment by this <hi>Depositum,</hi> or Thing committed to trust is, in the Scripture Phrase, <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Doctrine of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Scriptures.</note>
               <hi>Gospel of God, and of Christ,</hi> which is said to <hi>be committed to</hi> Pauls <hi>trust,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 11. and Gal. 2. 7. or <hi>the Doctrine of the Scriptures,</hi> being the <hi>platforme of sound Words and Doctrine</hi> according to Scripture; for such Doctrine alone is wholesome, sound and saving, as first discovers our disease. Secondly, Cures the same. And thirdly, prescribes means to preserve us in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall <note place="margin">Or Patterne of sound words ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> health and soundnesse of mind, being the <hi>Doctrine which is according to godlinesse,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 3.</p>
            <p>Now this Forme or Patterne of wholesome words, must be taken out of Scripture or be agreeable thereunto, from which it hath, and ever must have, its Authority; seeing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <note place="margin">On which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity alone. the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science of Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers vvill rest.</note> onely contains sound words and saving; neither will the Conscience rest in any thing but in this, <hi>Thus saith the Lord,</hi> not thus faith the Church, suppose of <hi>Rome,</hi> or thus we the Bishops and Clergy of <hi>Rome</hi> beleeve, because the Church, that is, we our selves have thus or thus said. Nay, nor simply thus <note place="margin">And no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the pretended either Church or Spirit.</note> saith the <hi>Spirit,</hi> unlesse it be according to this word: <hi>to the Law, and to the Testimony: if they speak not according to this Word, it is because there is no light in them,</hi> Esay 8. 19. 20. The true Beleever saith, I beleeve thus, and so, because Christ in his word, and according to it, hath thus spoken: I beleeve, therefore have I spoken. One conclusion well drawn out of Scripture, will give more contentment▪ comfort and satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the Concience, then an hundred out of mens autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, or pretended revelations without the word. For as <note place="margin">God himselfe being the prime truth, in it selfe, as his Word is to us, as our onely Rule.</note> God onely, who is the <hi>first and prime Goodnesse,</hi> is above all to be loved, and other things in and for him, seeing mans af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection can find no resting place till it pitch upon him; (for all earthly things leave it empty and unsatisfied:) so God onely is the <hi>first Truth;</hi> he himselfe for <hi>Being,</hi> as his <hi>Word,</hi> to us for knowledge: he is <hi>prima veritas Formalis,</hi> the first for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Truth, which is fundamentally, radically, and essentially in him; as his word is <hi>prima veritas Normalis,</hi> the prime or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205727:8"/> first and onely Rule of truth to us, he therefore alone and for himselfe is to be beleeved according to his word. A true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers judgement cannot rest but in the authority of God alone, as it is made known by his word, which is now (by Christ, by whom, as his essentiall word, and one in and from his bosome, he in these last dayes especially, speaks unto us, <hi>John</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. 2.) I say, is now fully, savingly, and suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently manifested to us in the holy Scriptures; so that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever rule or pattern is not taken out of, or agreeable to it, must not be listened unto. The Scripture contains that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one, true, and most ancient and first Doctrine, which was, and is delivered to the Church, and is primarily of Divine authority in it selfe, and <hi>Canonicall,</hi> that is, a Rule of Faith and Manners, of Faith and Love <hi>to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Other Formes of Doctrine, or of Faith and Love, which <note place="margin">Other Formes, Creeds and Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chismes have thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> use, as secondary, rules to us.</note> are taken out of it, are Rules secondarily, that is onely so farre as they agree with this prime Rule. Thus, such summary comprehensions of the Articles of our Faith as are in a more contracted manner, and according to the bare and naked Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of our Faith in the Apostles Creed; as also in such lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Creeds as are explications of that former; as in the <hi>Nicene, Constantinopolitan, Ephesine,</hi> and that of <hi>Athanasius,</hi> are Rules of Faith <hi>secundarily,</hi> which we of this our English Church have acknowledged and doe, as not dissenting from them, but acknowledging the same Faith which the ancients (according to those Creeds) did hold for five hundred, if not seven hundred yeares after Christ. The like we say of such Forms, Models of Doctrine and <hi>Catechismes</hi> which are extracted faithfully out of Scripture. For what is such a Forme or Catechisme, but a little Bible? and what is the Bible, but a large Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise? both include and contain the same truths; the one more scatteringly▪ yet originally and primarily; the other more sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily, and secondarily; and as may serve more fitly for order, method, and help of understanding and memory, and so for compendiousnesse of learning the Doctrine of the Scriptures, which otherwise contain many large explications, examples, and matters not Fundamentall or of that necessity to be known.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>second</hi> thing here meant, are <hi>Ministeriall gifts</hi> and <note place="margin">2. Ministeriall gifts.</note> abilities to dispence and divide this word aright with judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:205727:9"/> and such <hi>graces</hi> of God, which are given them by Jesus Christ, <hi>being in every thing enriched by him in all utterance, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich must be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ployed.</note>
               <hi>in all knowledge, whereby they come behi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d in no gift,</hi> which gifts <hi>Raul</hi> acknowledged to have been in the teachers of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> though they made but little good use of them, but abused them to nourish Factions and Schismes among them, whilst, though they had abil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty of utterance, yet they spake not all the same things, but nourished contentions among them; yea, Preached Christ, and painted him out (to the obscuring of his glory▪ power and wisedom) with excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Speech, and with the entising (or perswasible) words of humane wisedom, but not in the demonstration of the spirit and of power, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 4. 5.—7.—10. 11. &amp;c. <hi>and ch.</hi> 2. 1.—4. whereas he tells them that <hi>though there be diversitie of gifts, yet the same spirit—and that the manifestation of the Spirit is given to every man to profit withall,</hi> whether those gifts be the <hi>word of wisedom, the word of knowledge, the gift of faith, of healing, of working miracles, of prophesie, of discerning of spirits, of diverse kinds of tongues, of interpretation of tongues,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 4.—7. 8. 9. 10. These, and such as these, <hi>Paul</hi> calls that <hi>good thing committed to</hi> Timothy. 2 Tim. 1. 14. namely, the graces of the Spirit (which must also be kept by the holy Ghost which dwelleth in us) whereby Ministers are inabled unto their Function, and which they are to <hi>stir up,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 6. and to make use of for the spirituall good of others, not for vain ostentation, and to the adulterating of the truth and Gospel in the simplicity of the same. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd accounted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And being thus committed to Ministers, they, and we all, are taught, first that an <hi>account</hi> must be given of them. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that we must be <hi>faithfull</hi> in the distribution of them, being entrusted with them by God. And thirdly, that they must not be buried or suffered to lie idle, and be unimployed; the use and <hi>exercise</hi> of them is the way both to keep and to increase them, seeing <hi>to such as have, more shall be given.</hi> And herein spirituall gifts differ from worldly which perish and decay with use; but so doe not spirituall graces: they are lost onely whilest they are not imployed but, as it were, laid up in a napkin; as we see in him that hid his Talent, which wal therefore taken from him, and given to him that had▪ and well imployed five; and in such now adaies as for want of exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205727:9"/> their gifts, otherwise good, become more and more unfit for the Ministery▪ and unable to doe the work of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>third thing</hi> committed to the charge of <hi>Timothy,</hi> and included in it, is the <hi>Function and Office it selfe</hi> of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">3. <hi>The Office it selfe of</hi> teaching.</note> and dividing the word aright. <hi>This charge I commit unto thee Sonne</hi> Timothy <hi>according to the Prophesies which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on thee,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18. <hi>These things teach and exhort,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 2. <hi>I charge thee before God and the Lord Iesus Christ,—Preach the Word be instant in season, out of season, reprove, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, exhort with all long suffering and Doctrine,</hi> 2 Tim 4. 1. 2. These duties be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ong to his Office and charge yea you may see him specially charged to <hi>charge some that they teach no other Doctrine,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 3 4. and saith <hi>Paul,</hi> The <hi>things thou hast heard of me—the same commit thou to faithfull men, who shall be able to teach others also,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 2.</p>
            <p>From which places, and part of the Charge, we gather these <note place="margin">
                  <hi>VVhence vve learne two</hi> lessons.</note> two <hi>Lessons.</hi> First, That <hi>Gifts and Abilities alove, make not a Minister of Christ,</hi> (in an ordinary way) and that Preaching <note place="margin">1. That Gifts alone make not a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster.</note> of the word is not meerly an <hi>Act of Gifts,</hi> but of <hi>Office,</hi> so that Gifts and Calling, Matter and Forme must concurr to the constitution of him who exerciseth a Publick Ministery. So that if men <hi>will arise of themselves</hi> from among their Brethren, and fill their own hands, and run, being not sent, Its a Signe they are no true Prophets of God, (though we sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose they speak truth) as teaching without call or warrant, and such Order as God hath set in his Church, <hi>Ier.</hi> 23. 21. 22. 25. 32. and <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. 14. Christ himselfe was called of God, as was <hi>Aaron, Heb.</hi> 5. 4. 5. And saith this our Apostle, <hi>Rom,</hi> 10. 15. <hi>How should they Preach</hi> (he saith not without gifts, though <note place="margin">Though the gifts of private m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and vvomen may and must be used, yet they make them n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Ministers.</note> these be required but) <hi>unlesse they be sent?</hi> Its granted, that every Member of the Church may use his own Talent, as a Member, and in the communion of Saints, to the good▪ of others, in their own Families and relations, but not as a <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Instrument</hi> of the Church, and by vertue of any mission or commission from God, such as is given to Ministers sent of God, with promise of a blessing, as <hi>Math.</hi> 28. 19. 20. I doubt <note place="margin">The Ministery is a distinct Calling from others.</note> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but that in great Corporations and Counties, there are, or may be sound some who are neither Aldermen, Justices, or in Office, who yet if they were called, were sufficiently able for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205727:10"/> parts and abilities, to discharge the trust committed to them. Its not a mans able parts makes any, suppose Steward of your house, but your committing the Keyes into his hand; neither do Abilities, but Commission makes an Ambassadour. When the Ministers of <hi>England</hi> have pleaded, (among many other things to prove their Calling) <hi>the gifts which God had given them,</hi> those of the separation themselves have shewed some scruple in the point, and are wont to tell them, <hi>Qualification is no calling;</hi> and so we say, that every one that is fit to be a Minister, is not therefore called to be one. But he that is <note place="margin">In vvhich yet Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisteri may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by and from their gifts graciously and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually imploied.</note> otherwise called to be a Minister, and hath had sufficient triall of his abilities, and of good successe, and Gods blessing on his gifts, in the conversion of many Soules, may, to his comfort, and to the further assurance of his calling from God, as well as from man, pleade the same with such as question it, or <hi>seek a Proofe of Christ speaking in them,</hi> appealing to such (as the Seale of his Ministery) whom he hath begotten by his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery again to God. This was <hi>Pauls</hi> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and he was so farre put to it, that he was either to make good his Call and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery from that Argument, or to conclude them unsound Christians or <hi>reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13. 3.—5. and 2 Cor. 3. 1. 2. 3.</p>
            <p>But how comes it to passe now adayes▪ that the Calling of such, who have both their gifts from God, and a Call so farre <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reproofe <hi>of upstars</hi> teachers.</note> also from the Peoples acceptance of them, is so much questio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by those that maintain, That <hi>any one sufficiently gifted may</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Master</hi> Seaman <hi>in his Epistle to the</hi> Reader.</note>
               <hi>Preach, and he whom the People shall accept of as a Minister to them, is thereby made a Minister?</hi> Here thus farre the tearmes are equall, and we may pleade both these as well as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Yet see the bold presumption of many, who intrude into the work of the Ministery (upon what grounds, or to what ends, I leave others to guesse at) and (to Preach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves into the calling) indeavour to Preach, or (by revilings and aspersions) to Prate others out of it: these being such, for the most part as declare themselves false. Prophers, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in (under pretence and name of <hi>New Lights)</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving <hi>old and damned errours,</hi> as well-becomming such <hi>inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate</hi> and <hi>unordained</hi> Preachers, drawing also the itching Ears of the People after them, and withdrawing them, by separation, from that Ministery, unto which (unlesse they be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205727:10"/> reprobate indeed concerning the Faith, and unsound converts) they owe themselves and all they are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From the former point; That the Office of teaching is part of this charge, we gather this <hi>second Instruction,</hi> that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. That an outward Call from Men, and</hi> Ordination <hi>is also needfull.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>inward call from God, an outward and Ministeriall Call from man; or Ordination,</hi> especially in an ordinary way, and in a setled Church, is <hi>necessary,</hi> and not to be omitted, as we have briefly shewed <note n="*" place="margin">Pag 6.</note> already. Where though <hi>Timothy</hi> were by Prophesies before on him, and by revelation from God, signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied unto the Church to be designed and called to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery, (as others the like, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 1. 2. 3. though in a case somewhat different) yet the <hi>charge of teaching,</hi> was by <hi>Paul committed to his trust,</hi> and that <hi>by the laying on of the hands of the Presbytery,</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 18. with 4. 14. and 2 Tim. 1. 6. This <note place="margin">Being according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Order.</note>
               <hi>Order</hi> we find in Scripture, <hi>Christ</hi> the chiefe Pastor, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 25. (in whom is the power of making Ministers,) Ordaines twelve Apostles, <hi>Mark</hi> 3. 14. The <hi>Apostles</hi> as next to him and as his Stewards and in his absence, and by his direction and command <hi>Ordayned</hi> Elders, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. And to <hi>Elders,</hi> and not to any other, the Apostles from God, and in his name, and by his appointment, give Power of Ordination of other Elders <hi>successively.</hi> So that though they, thus Ordaining, (which is objected by some) were <hi>extraordinary</hi> Persons for gifts and calling, yet that was fit and necessary in the first setling of Government: neither are such gifts and calling needfull now in their Successors (for then we should not Preach their Doctrine left us in writing, in which as well as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>That Elders succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sively</hi> should <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Elders.</hi>
               </note> in Ruling, and setling of Government their calling was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary.) Now they setled Government in every Church <hi>then</hi> in their times, in which was an <hi>uniformity,</hi> both in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Doctrine and discipline, as <hi>Paul,</hi> speaketh of both, useth these expressions, <hi>As I teach every where, in every Church,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 17. and, <hi>So Ordain I in all Churches,</hi> 1 Cor. 7. 17. And speaking more expressely of disorders in the Church, he concludes, <hi>But if any man seem to be contentious, we have no such custome, neither the Churches of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 16. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare also ver. 2. 3. 4. howsoever as is acknowledged by some of the separation, <hi>The Churches of the New Testament conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing</hi>
               <note place="margin">Robinson <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Seaman, <hi>in his Vindication,</hi> p. 56.</note>
               <hi>and abiding,</hi> (to which may be added, <hi>revived</hi> and <hi>renued)</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:205727:11"/>
               <hi>in that State, Faith and Order, wherein they were set, and establi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed by the Lord in the hands of his servants the Apostles and Evangelists, were to receive their Ministers constantly by s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on after a sort, namely so farre as that all succeeding Ministers were to be Ordained by Ministers, and not otherwise.</hi> As the Apostles then Ordained in all Churches, and Ordained them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves or appointed others to Ordain, as <hi>Titus, Tit.</hi> 1. 5. and <hi>Timothy,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 5. 22. So by virtue of that Apostolicall both Practise and Ordination we conclude that, the Ministe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being an Office or Calling, the way of entrance into it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by him that appointed the Office it selfe is, and ought to be that Power of Ordination which God hath committed to the <hi>Elders</hi> of the Church to whom it belongs to Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute and Ordaine other Elders, who thereby receive a <hi>potesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Mission,</hi> and their Office of Preaching, and of doing other duties proper to the Ministery. This Power some make to be onely in and from the Election of the People, without Ordination by Imposition of hands, which they say is not <note place="margin">This Povver is not in the People. Election and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovved them, but not Ordination.</note> essentiall to the manner of entrance. <hi>Essentiall?</hi> No more is Baptisme, or the Lords Supper to the Being of a Christian, or to Salvation, yet of excellent use, and of clear Institution.</p>
            <p>But for <hi>Ordination;</hi> we Reade, That when one was to be <hi>Ordained</hi> an Apostle in stead of <hi>Judas,</hi> or <hi>made</hi> and constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <note place="margin">Genesthai.</note> a Witnesse with the rest, of Christs Resurrection accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to a motion made from God by <hi>Peter,</hi> (who stood up in the midst of the Disciples, who were an hundred and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) <note place="margin">Acts 15. 22. 23.</note> Its said they <hi>appointed</hi> two, <hi>They,</hi> the multitude; <hi>appointed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hestesan.</note> or set before them, whereof the one was to be Ordained or <hi>made</hi> a Witnesse: by <hi>whom?</hi> but by the Apostles▪ after the <note place="margin">As in a like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance.</note> Lord had by Lot made known whom he had chosen. And this was done in this Order: <hi>First, Peter</hi> propounds to them, as from the Lord, and as Moderator of the Assembly, what was to be done. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the Multitude or People pitch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and chuse out of, and from among themselves, two, whom they set and presented before the Apostles. This <hi>done, then</hi> they betake themselves to <hi>Prayer;</hi> for this was the great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of moment, and greater then Election of the People; Then <hi>fourthly,</hi> the Lot falls upon <hi>Matthias.</hi> And <hi>lastly,</hi> he is <hi>Ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and ever after numbred with the eleven.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:205727:11"/>
            <p> But you will say, this was in the choise of an Apostle, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Instance given in the</hi> Ordination of Deacons; <hi>in which the people had the power onely of election▪ or nomination.</hi>
               </note> know that the like order was observed, and the Apostles and Ministers of the Church Ordayned men, even to the meanest <hi>Office</hi> it selfe; which Ordination belongs to them and not to the People alone, whose office is to elect, chuse or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, but not to Ordain. This is plain by <hi>Acts</hi> 6. in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment of the office of <hi>Deacon-ship,</hi> to seven chosen men, where we shall see, That election of the People is but <hi>prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory</hi> (even in that very lowest <hi>office,)</hi> Their <hi>office</hi> was to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and present some persons from among themselves to that <hi>office,</hi> who being considered of, tryed and approved by the Apostles, were accordingly to be <hi>Ordayned.</hi> See these things more distinctly and ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erve the <hi>order▪</hi> which then was, and still ought to be in the Church of God▪ and the subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation between officers and people. The authority of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Church together (upon a speciall occasion) was in the Apostles <hi>vers.</hi> 2. Then <hi>the twelve ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the multitude of the Disciples unto them, and said, &amp;c.</hi> They also communicated their counsell with the people, nothing was done without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son and order. <hi>Look yee out among you seven men—whom we may appoint over this businesse.</hi> Where we see, The People are allowed to chuse nominate, and present, and so farre to have <note place="margin">No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of ordination</note> a common suffrage to chuse into this publique <hi>office.</hi> Onely the Apostles appoint and ordain. And this is a good middle way to prevent <hi>confusion</hi> in the <hi>People,</hi> and <hi>tyranny</hi> in the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers.</hi> This example shews <hi>first,</hi> how the Disciples and People <hi>before Election,</hi> must consider and look out fit men, both for number and qualification (they are supposed to be wise, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, diligent, in their choise, and conscionable in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending such onely as are fit.) Secondly, how, after their election, they must shew their approbation, and make their presentation: <hi>For when they had ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sen</hi> Stephen, <hi>and the rest, they set them before the Apostles</hi> ver. 5. 6. Thus farre the People or Multitude had power, so that if they made not a good choise they might thank themselves. The next thing is, that now after election but before ordination (as the chiefe businesse of all) they joyne in <hi>Prayer:</hi> after which the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles (not onely as <hi>Apostles,</hi> but as <hi>Elders</hi> of that Church, then and there gathered) approving of the Peoples approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:205727:12"/>
               <hi>Ordained and laid their ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se</hi> which were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented, <hi>ver.</hi> 6, Now if such <hi>Ordination</hi> to the meanest <hi>office</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the Church (which yet is call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d a <hi>Businesse,</hi> or a necessary work) be needfull how much more to the high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, (now in a setled Church) and to the office of Elders and <note place="margin">Much lesse are they to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Govern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ver to Elders wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> belong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Elder, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves.</note> Preaching Ministers who are not to receive their governing Power from the People or Church, though elected by them, for which they have no Commission from Christ, such as <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> have, whom the Scripture makes distinct from the Flock and People, who are commanded to be sub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ect and obedient to their Bishops, Pastors, and Rulers, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 24. It belongs therefore to <hi>Elders</hi> to ordain <hi>Elders,</hi> not to any unofficied man. I shall onely by one place (now) shew that the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> in Planting of the Churches, as that of <hi>Ephesus,</hi> and setling a way how <hi>Timothy</hi> and others should behave themselves in the house of God, gives <hi>Timothy</hi> a <hi>charge,</hi> which he also was to commit, by way of like charge, to faithfull men and so from one to another,) whereof this <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 2.</note> was part, <hi>Lay hands s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ddenly on no man, neither be partaker of other mens sinnes.</hi> Where we have either a direct <hi>Precept,</hi> or the <hi>duty presupposed,</hi> for <hi>Ordination</hi> by <hi>Elders:</hi> the restriction <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Which is shewed out of</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 21. 22.</note> or manner of doing it (that he must not doe it <hi>suddenly</hi> or rashly) confirmes not onely the lawfulnesse (which I take such as are for the peoples power this way, will not easily grant) but the <hi>Office and Duty of Ordination by laying on of hands:</hi> which they are to doe, but <hi>not rashly</hi> or <hi>suddenly,</hi> (without due triall and knowledge) though the people should <hi>elect</hi> rashly: Yea doubtlesse, in such case, the <hi>Presbytery</hi> is to <hi>reject</hi> that rash <hi>Election,</hi> and make it void. To try and judge of the sufficiency of able Preaching Ministers in all points, cannot be thought to belong to the body of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (scarce one of many hundreds being of ability so to doe) which yet such as <hi>Ordain</hi> are bound to doe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 5. 6. to 12. Now the charge given <hi>Timothy,</hi> is not against hasty <hi>Election,</hi> (but <hi>Ordination)</hi> as in all reason it should have been, if <hi>Election</hi> had onely or chiefly made the officer: but we see the charge is more expresse, that <hi>Ordination</hi> rather then <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> should not suddenly and hastily be made. Not to say <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plain Platforme</hi> pag. 8.</note> that the Scripture speaks much and plainly for <hi>Ordination,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:205727:12"/> but little or nothing, or but obscurely for popular Election of Elders: yea, I might add, if that power by Christ or his Apostles had been left to the body of beleevers. It had been much easier to have writ to the Churches, that they should ordain their own Elders, then either to have travelled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, or to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> for that purpose, as <note place="margin">Acts 14. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 22. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 15.</p>
            <p>But in this Point more need not be said. Onely I will conclude, that if any, upon a contrary conceit, or upon any other prejudice, shall, either himselfe being a Minister, lay down, (at the peoples feet) and so renounce, his Ministery, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formerly ordained a Minister, in, and of our Church of <note place="margin">To lay a mans for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nistery at the peoples feet—an, unworthy act.</note>
               <hi>England,</hi> and then take it up as from them again; or, by so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or otherwise shall seek not onely to make <hi>Ordination</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary for the future, but null and voyd for the time past: I say, I shall account it a most unworthy act in such a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and an argument of weaknesse, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llinesse, if not malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse in such other, whosoever, as would thus traduce, or question the lawfulnesse of the Calling of us Ministers for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly <hi>Ordained</hi> by Presbyters or Bishops and so make it a pretence why they will not heare us, either at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise then as gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted men, and as they would heare any the meanest and most illiterate Trades-man, if they conceive him to have gifts.</p>
            <p>The chiefe <hi>objection</hi> or pretence which such make against us, <note place="margin">The choise objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ered.</note> is that our <hi>Ordination</hi> was and is by <hi>Bishops</hi> or by such as had their <hi>Ordination</hi> from <hi>Bishops,</hi> as they from Popish Bishops <note place="margin">And it shewed.</note> formerly and therefore it is <hi>Antichristian,</hi> and we <hi>Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Ministers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I answer 1. This is an Antichristian censure and <note place="margin">Ansvver to the <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>be</hi> in Epist. <hi>That</hi> Ordination <hi>is no</hi> Antichristi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, <hi>though used, or abused by Popish Bishops and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats,</hi> ibid. p. 85.</note> ought no more to move us then (as one expresseth it) to find <hi>Rahell</hi> and <hi>Thamar</hi> among those, through whose loines the naturall Succession of our blessed Saviour is propagated from <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Though Bishops seem to be a superiour <hi>Order,</hi> (and some of them made such a claime) yet in point of <hi>ordination,</hi> they <note place="margin">1. They ordained as Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>byters.</note> are and were to be looked upon as Presbyters and Elders, and not as a superiour <hi>order,</hi> which neither our Church or State did ever so declare them to be, but declared against them. Nay,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:205727:13"/> they were first Elders before they were Bishops, and of Elders were made Bishops in way of <hi>accumulation,</hi> not in way of <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,</hi> as if they so ceased to be Elders; and if they erroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously thought themselves a superiour order to Presbyters their errour could not make them no Presbyters. And therefore Bishops onely and alone were never authorized to lay on hands, excluding Presbyters, but together with them▪ as fellow Presbyters, (as also <hi>Peter</hi> writes and stiles himselfe. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 1.) Prelacy did no more annihilate their being Presbyters, then Pharisaisme did the Jewish Priesthood: Nay it would be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered whether the Papists themselves make no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Bishops and Presbyters one Order, who (as we are told) judge, that if a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Platforme,</hi> pag. 16.</note> Deacon should be made a Bishop, <hi>per saltum,</hi> he hath no power to ordain Presbyters.</p>
            <p n="3">3. which alone may be abundantly sufficient. <hi>Ordination</hi> being, as is shewed, of primitive Institution, to be of use in the <note place="margin">3. Ordination was long before Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ arose, and that still continues (being reformed) by Divine and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolical Institution.</note> Churches in succeeding ages, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o continue in the Churches of God in all ages and places. Such abuses, as in former times, did any way adhere through mens corruption, unto it, can no way null or make voyd that Institution, especially after it is purged of such abuse, and there faylings, in and by such as received such ordinations, if any were, repented of: true Repentance, after faylings being, in Gods account, equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to Innocency; otherwise woe to all true penitents and converts. Though therefore ordination came through the hands, even of Popish Bishops, yet neither doth it make their calling and order lawfull, or the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> a true Church; or yet ordination now, (according to Gods Word and first In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution) unlawfull. The Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though we should deny it to be a true Church, yet it is not hereby justified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause of the lawfulnesse of Ordination because in a false Church there may be something true. And we say that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church was at first a true Church, and had divine Truths and ordinances in it which (good at first) came through the hands even of Popish and Antichristian Bishops, and were much aspersed with their Leaven which yet we now (having reformed the abuses) still hold, and doe, and must maintain, by virtue of the originall of them, and of the Primitive Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, purging out (or if guilty) repenting of the same.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:205727:13"/> Such Ordinances of God were <hi>Baptisme,</hi> and this of <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or <hi>Imposition of hands,</hi> both which are joyned together among the <hi>Principles of the foundation spoken of,</hi> Hebr. 6. 1. <note place="margin">As doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Baptisme.</note> and both were even from the times of the Apostles in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> long b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore she became Apostate, yea and have been there continued to this day, howsoever mingled with many corruptions and inventions of their own being in themselves of God and no humane Inventions neither of them brought in by Antichrist into the Temple of God, but had a Being therein before Antichrist sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e there. Should we then, because these ordinances were corrupted by Antichrist, call them Antichristian, when, and after they are purged from whatsoever of Antichrist was in them? or shall wee look on them as nulled and made voyd by Popish Bishops to all that now partake thereof that there should be conceived any need of the Iteration or repeating of either of them? And I the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>There needs no ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration either of</hi> Baptisme <hi>or</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</note> rather speak of them both together (though the one onely doe properly belong to my present argument) because the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists</hi> are alike against both▪ upon the same grounds, as sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing that Antichrist hath utterly destroyed all Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances so that there was not true <hi>Baptisme</hi> reteined and had among them: and so for <hi>Ordination.</hi> Whereupon as they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n to Baptize themselves again, so to account all ordination, which they conceive to be derived from Antichrist, to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichristian and voyd; and to require that if any formerly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained should be called to exercise his Function in any of their separate Congregations, he should utterly renounce his former ordination (though originally from God) and receive a new Call and Power from the People, or by a new Imposition of hands, But we, though opposite to Popery and Prelacy, doe, with much better reason, judge both Baptisme and Ordination valid, and not to be changed, whilest we look to their first In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution from God, and onely purge them from the defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they received under that generall defection and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stasie in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> by reforming what was amisse therein, putting difference between such Fundamental Truths first received from God, which God did preserve when Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ raigned, raged, and raved most, such (among others) were the essence of Baptisme, and the essence of a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:205727:14"/> dispencing it, so that even when the Church was in the Wildernesse, her Pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s did feed her there <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. 6.—14.</p>
            <p>But enough to satisfie the indifferent Reader in this point, and to leave convinced the peevish and perves<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, who must in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy their own fancies and will, and who will yet separate from us as Antichristian which reproach, the Lord lay not to their charge. Let them also see how they can answer it, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to acknowledge the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and her Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, to be true Churches, and yet separate themselves from the same.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Now we proceed to the <hi>fourth Thing,</hi> included in the <hi>Charge</hi> given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and committed to the keeping of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he fourth thing in his charge, is.</hi> The are of Soules.</note> Ministers; and that is, <hi>The ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and charge of Soules,</hi> and the Salvation thereof, as the chiefe end of their gifts and calling. Ministers are by Vertue of their Calling, <hi>Keepers</hi> of Gods Church and betrusted with the Soules of his People▪ commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their charge. The winning or losing of Soules depends much what upon them, upon their diligence or negligence, (even the Salvation of such Soules as the Sonne of God hath purchased with his blood:) They had need <hi>take heed unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20. 28.</note> (and to their lives and conversations) <hi>as also unto their Doctrine,</hi> that <hi>they continue therein;</hi> for in so doing (and not otherwise) <hi>they both save themselves, and those that heare them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 4 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>Relations</hi> shew them to be <hi>Keepers.</hi> The Church of God is Gods <hi>Flock;</hi> and they by the holy Ghost are made <note place="margin">Which a shewed by he relations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ween Ministers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd their people.</note>
               <hi>Overseers,</hi> to feed the same <hi>Acts</hi> 20 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. So <hi>John</hi> 21. 15. 16. 17. <hi>Feed my Sheep, feed my Lambs</hi> and so they keep them in health and soundnesse. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Church is <hi>Gods house and Family,</hi> and they are <hi>Stewards of the Mysteries of God</hi> and <hi>Rulers over his house, to give them their portion of meat in due season,</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 1. Luke 12. 42. It is a <hi>City,</hi> and they <hi>Sentinels</hi> and <hi>Watchmen</hi> to keep it in safety, and to give warning, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3. 17. Its his <hi>Temple,</hi> and they not onely <hi>Builders,</hi> of it (under him) out of the rude quarries and Woods; but also <hi>Keepers of holy things,</hi> belonging unto it: as of old. The Ark and holy things were committed to the Custody of holy Persons onely. Yea, the Church is <hi>Gods Vineyard</hi> and <hi>Husband<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> and they <hi>Keepers and Dressers</hi> of it. Yea <hi>lastly,</hi> it is Christs <hi>Spouse;</hi> and their <hi>office</hi> is, in a holy jealousie to watch over her, and so to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:205727:14"/> keep her, that her <hi>mind may not</hi> (by the subtilty of <hi>Satan,</hi> and seducers) <hi>be corrupted from the simplicity that is in Christ,</hi> but that they may present her a chast Virgin to Christ: not suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 2. 3.</note> her to be corrupted by others, much lesse corrupting her themselves.</p>
            <p>Therefore great and dangerous is their charge, if they look <note place="margin">The charge is gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> not well to it. Its a Charge, and Burthen formidable, and terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Angells themselves, and heavy enough for their shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. They had need be carefull, for they <hi>Watch</hi> for the Soules of such, over whom they have the rule and must give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 17. They had need be wise, for this rule and government over Soules, is, <hi>Ars Artium,</hi> the great Art of all other Arts as one calls it.</p>
            <p>As this shews the <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of the Calling, so the <hi>Burthen and Duty of it.</hi> And for some <hi>Directions</hi> to this duty, <note place="margin">Some directions be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to keep Soules.</note> of keeping the Soules of Gods People committed to us, to that which hath been said in the beginning, in the particulars of this Charge given by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and in him to all Ministers. I will briefly subjoyne these.</p>
            <p>We doe, and must endeavour to keep Soules.</p>
            <p n="1">1 By <hi>Preaching Gods pure Word,</hi> and it alone, unto them: thus, by taking heed to our Doctrine, as also to our lives and selves; we save our selves, and them that heare us, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 16. otherwise we <hi>bring no profit to them,</hi> Jerem. 23. 22.—28.—32. But doe <hi>overthrow their Faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 17. 18. And this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <hi>Wisedome and Diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>By strengthning the weak,</hi> healing the sick, binding up the broken, &amp;c. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 4.—16. This requires <hi>Residence</hi> and <hi>Attendance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. By not suffering them to be spoyled by the Wolfe or Fox, against which we must cry, to chase them away, yea, and <hi>must goe up into the gaps, and make up the hedge for Gods Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3 4 5.</note> where its broken down, and <hi>so stand in the Battell, in the day of the Lord</hi> (against all enemies of his peoples Faith and Soules) <hi>earnestly contending for the Faith, which was once deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the Saints,</hi> confuting errours, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. and with <note place="margin">Jude, vers. 3</note>
               <hi>David,</hi> to our power, delivering Christs Sheep out of the mouth of the Lyon, and pawes of the Beare. And this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires <hi>Conscience, Zeale,</hi> Ability and soundnesse of judgement.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:205727:15"/> 4. By commending them by <hi>Prayer</hi> to God, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 23. This requires <hi>humility</hi> and <hi>selfe-distrust.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. By being ready, if need be, to be <hi>Sacrificed for them, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Cor. 12. 15. 1 Thes. 2. 7. 8. This requ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es true <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These things we should see to, least, as in King <hi>Ahabs</hi> case, our Soules go for theirs, if either through sloth, unnecessary absence, unsoundnesse, couldnesse, feare, pride▪ &amp;c. we cause or suffer them to perish. Every Minister when he enters on his charge, becomes liable to account, and his Soule stands as a paune, for the Soules of others; he may say to each hearer, <hi>my Soule and Life</hi> (stands) <hi>for thine:</hi> I must answer for thee, if thou miscarry, as well as thou for thy selfe, for God layes <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> antipsuches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> son.</note> such a charge on each. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3. 18. which is according to the law of things committed to trust, <hi>Levit.</hi> 6. 2. 4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. 7. 10. In such case, he is an happy man that can truely say with <hi>Paul,</hi> (when he comes to dye) <hi>I am pure from the blood of all men: for I have not shunned to declare unto you all the Counsell of God,</hi> Acts 20. 26. 27. And happy are such Sheep as have such Keepers.</p>
            <p>And this may serve for the <hi>Vse</hi> of this last and <hi>fourth Point</hi> of the <hi>third</hi> branch, which was, <hi>What</hi> this thing committed to Trust, is.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>fourth</hi> or <hi>last</hi> particular concerning this <hi>Charge,</hi> is the <hi>Charge it selfe, or Duty of</hi> keeping it. <hi>Keep that which is</hi>
               <note place="margin">4. The fourth thing in the Charge, is the Charge it selfe.</note>
               <hi>committed to thy trust.</hi> This, as it shewes, that all Ministers are <hi>Depositaries</hi> and have much committed to their Trust, so their Duty is faithfully to see to the discharge of the same, and to keep it, according to the foure particulars named.</p>
            <p>But because we have already made Use as we went along of the <hi>three last,</hi> (as of the imployment of their gifts, of way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on their Office, and expecting a Call from man as well as from God, and of their charge of Soules.) I will now one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly presse the Duty, and make more speciall use of it, as it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the <hi>keeping of the purity of Doctrine committed to their trust,</hi> which I conceive is in the first place, or chiefly meant <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Or Duty of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, especially of keeping the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of</hi> Doctrine, Vincent Leri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ns.</note> in the charge, as appears by the next words, <hi>avoyding, &amp;c.</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by the contrary, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 3. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>▪ 6. and 6. 3.</p>
            <p>And then the Duty is this, That seeing this <hi>Depositum</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:205727:15"/>
               <hi>Catholicae fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> talentum,</hi> this thing committed to trust is the Talent of the true Catholique Faith, and that true and sound Doctrine is a matter of trust, therefore it ought to be kept faithfully and carefully.</p>
            <p>Here I shall shew <hi>first</hi> in what <hi>Mannor</hi> it must be kept, <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why? <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the <hi>Ʋses</hi> of the Point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It must be kept in it selfe <hi>intirely,</hi> in regard of the parts of it without either <hi>adding</hi> to it, <hi>altering</hi> of it, or <hi>taking</hi> from <note place="margin">1. <hi>Divine and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolicall Doctrine must be kept Intir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> vvithout</note> it. It is a <hi>Rule</hi> and a <hi>Standard,</hi> and therefore perfect, straight and full. Its <hi>Christs Testament,</hi> and admits not of any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, addition, or detraction. The Church of Christ being <note place="margin">1. Diminution.</note> the <hi>Pillar</hi> of truth and stay of it, is, and ought to be a wary, carefull, and faithfull Keeper of all and every truth commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to her charge, changing nothing in the same, diminishing nothing, adding nothing. It (performing its trust) takes and cuts off nothing necessary, adds nothing superfluous, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loseth nothing of her own, usurps nothing belonging not to her, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>If once liberty were granted to lay aside or wave any need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full truth, yea, or any parcell of it, what danger would ensue of <note place="margin">Vincent Lerin. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> the cutting off, and abolishing Religion it selfe? For by like reason one sound truth after another might and would be (as it were out of custome, and as by a Law) abolished, and lose its credit and authority; and consequently the whole Truth and Religion of God should be rejecteds, as by wofull effects we see it in these our dayes, in such as at length are falne to question, at least, if not deny, not onely some particular and manifest Truthes, but the Old Testament, and all authority and proofe fetched thence, yea, the whole Scriptures and their divine authority.</p>
            <p>And so again, if once new and old, extraneous and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mestick▪ holy and prophane, begin to be <hi>mingled</hi> together, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Altering or min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling.</note> what in the Church will any long while be preserved pure, whole, or immaculate? whilest in processe of time there will be stewes of wicked and filthy errours, where formerly had <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> been a sacred Chappel of Christ, holy and uncorruted truth.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>addition</hi> to the Doctrine of the Scriptures, as the onely Rule of Faith, we say truely, that <hi>Fidei Incrementum</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Addition.</note>
               <hi>est Fidei Decrementum,</hi> to adde is to take from the Faith: And <hi>Nihil ultrà scire est omnia scire:</hi> to know nothing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:205727:16"/> beyond that Rule, is to know all things.</p>
            <p>Now if you say God added the <hi>Prophets</hi> to <hi>Moses,</hi> and the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he later parts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cripture adde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>othing of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ance to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Evangelists</hi> and <hi>Apostles</hi> writing to both. <hi>I answer,</hi> This was no addition of things or Doctrines, so much as beside, much lesse contrary or repugnant to ancient truths, neither was it in the substance, but in cucumstances, and clearer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestations and applications of the same truths. And so we say, the larger Creeds, add no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing to that of the Apostles, but by way of fuller and clearer explication. And so we may say the like of the <hi>Articles</hi> or Doctrine of our Churches Faith, though they exceed the number of twelve, yet they are not increased in or according to <hi>Principles,</hi> but onely <hi>Conclusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi>
               <note place="margin">True Doctrine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th, not in Principles but in Conclusions.</note> they (as our Doctrines, which we gather and raise in our Preaching from the Scripture, though many and severall) are but so many Conclu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ions from the same Principles which are in the Apostles Creed, and firstly in the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But you will say,</hi> Will you have Religion stand at a stay, and admit of no progresse, proficiency, or growth? Not so neither. I wish there were that growth which should, yea, and might be, and I hope none is so envious to man, or hatefull to God, who seeks to hinder it.</p>
            <p>But then, saith one, let it truely be a growth of Faith, and <note place="margin">The growth of knowledge and Doctrine is (and must be) onely as the grovvth of a Childs body, the Person still remaining the same in Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in old Age.</note> not a permutation or exchange of it. It belongs to the <hi>growth</hi> of any thing that it be inlarged and amplified in it selfe: but to <hi>change</hi> that it be changed and turned from one thing to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wherefore let there be a growth and increase to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most, for degree not onely in the understanding, knowledge, and wisedome of each particular man, but of all, and of the whole Church, according to the degrees and progresse of age and time: but then let it be in, and within its own kind, and the same opinion or truth maintained▪ and in the same sence and meaning of it. Let Religion grow as humane bodies doe, which remain the same▪ whether little▪ and in childhood, or great▪ and in riperage: The same men, and no other) become old; who were young men; and though the state and stature of the same, or of any one man be changed with age, yet the nature and person is one and the same. The parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in a sucking child and the severall members are but little, but in young men, well grown, they are greater, yet still they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:205727:16"/> are the selfe same, nothing shews it selfe in men when they are old which was not, from the beginning in the power and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Seed; nothing new is brought to light in time in old men, which long before lay not hid in them when they were young. This is the true and kind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y order of growth in men; but if a child should, whiles it seems to grow, be turned to another shape or nature then its own, or any member be either wanting, or added to the number of humane members, either the whole body perisheth, or becoms Monstrous and prodigious or at b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st, is much weakned.</p>
            <p>Such a growth should be in our knowledge, and in all divine truths, which with years are more strengthened and confirmed, by time inlarged and with age resined; yet should they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main uncorrupted, and full and perfect in the measures of all their parts, and as it were in their proper senses, and severall members, so <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t they admit not of mixture or change, lose nothing which may be called a propriety, permit not any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of definition.</p>
            <p>This then belongs to our duty, to see that the seed of Faith and Doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owne in the Word, like good Wheat, remain so still, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and Darnell be not mistaken for it: and that others after us may, in a more abundant manner reape nothing but Wheat without altering any thing of the nature of it; let us endeavour that ancient truths, in these latter dayes▪ be more looked into, more illustrated polished made use of; but farre be it from us to change▪ mang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, and deface them. Let them by us receive more evidence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinction▪ but let us be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e they retain their fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nesse, intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and propriety.</p>
            <p>O <hi>Timothy</hi> then, ó Doctor, ô thou expounder of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ods Word, <note place="margin">Doctrine <hi>would be taught more c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>early every day.</hi>
               </note> (saith the so enamed Author) if God of his grace hath fitted thee, as another <hi>Besaleel</hi> to help in the building of his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, grave these precious gemmes of divine Truths, fit them together faithfully, adorn them wisely, adde splendour, light, grace, and beauty to them. <hi>Intelligatur te exponente illustriùs, quod ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a obscurius cred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>batur;</hi> Let that be more clearly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstood by thy Exposition, which formerly was more obscure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeved<hi>—eadem tamen quae dedicisti ita do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>▪ ut cum dicas novè, non dicas nova;</hi> Yet so teach what thou hast been taught,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:205727:17"/> that whilest thou <hi>speakest after a new manner, way, or method, thou speak and utter no new things;</hi> and, as elsewhere that what <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap.</hi> 32.</note> formerly was beleeved barely and simply (and as it were by an implicite Faith) may afterward with more diligence be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; that what was formerly more coldly, and with lesse life Preached, the same now may be with greater instance, and earnestly Preached, &amp;c. And all this belongs to the Duty in the Text of Keeping, and the manner of Keeping that which is committed to us. It would be kept <hi>intire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Reasons</hi> hereof are these. 1. Because it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a matter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our <hi>trust▪</hi> and therefore need be kept safe, pure, and <note place="margin"> 2. <hi>Why</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> sure; <hi>Custodi propter fures, propter inimicos &amp;c.</hi> Keep it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause <note place="margin"> 1. <hi>It is a matter of</hi> Trust.</note> of Theeves: It hath many enemies also, who, whilest men sleep, sow their Tares among that good Wheat, which the Sonne of Man hath sowne in his Field. </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>First</hi> know it is not <hi>Inventum, sed traditum;</hi> not a thing invented by thee, but delivered in trust to thee; that <note place="margin">And Therefore 1. No Invention of Man, but a thing delivered to him.</note> which thou hast <hi>received,</hi> not which thou hast <hi>devised;</hi> no matter of humane Wit, but of divine Doctrine whereof thou art not Authour, but Keeper; not a Master, but a Schollar; not a Leader simply but a Follower, And thou must bring in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of thine own head.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>nature of things committod to trust,</hi> and the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>them</hi> is such that they be kept without alteration dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution, <note place="margin">2. To be restored as it was received by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pure, without Adulterating it.</note> imbezeling, or corrupting of them; and that they be restored the sime, and as we received them. Therefore saith <hi>Paul,</hi> or God himselfe may say, <hi>Aurum accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sti, aurum redde;</hi> thou hast received Gold, restore Gold I will not thou givest one thing in stead of another; <hi>Nolo pro auro aut impudenter plumbum, aut fraudulenter aeramenta supponas.</hi> I will not that thou shouldest foyst in and restore either <hi>impudently</hi> Lead, or <hi>frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently,</hi> Copper and Brasse. <hi>Nolo auri speciem, sed naturam planè.</hi> I will admit of no shews of Gold, but of the pure nature of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It being a matter onely of trust, it is to be <hi>kept but for a time,</hi> it will be called for again, and accounts must be given <note place="margin">3. To be kept by us onely for a time, when we must be accountable.</note> of it, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 13. 17. and as in the unjust Steward. So 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 17. Whether therefore willingly or unwillingly (or not at all) we due discharge our trust, the dispensation of the Gospel being once committed to our trust, will be required of us, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:205727:17"/> accounts must be given either with joy or griefe, and woe to such as being thus charged with the Gospel, either Preach it not at all, or corrupted, unwillingly, or for hire onely, and base ends. What Soules are lost through their default, or what good, through their carelesnesse is not done, will be required at their hands, as <hi>Jacob</hi> made good to <hi>Laban</hi> what was lost, or torn of those Sheep wherof he was made the Keeper, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 39.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It would be considered also, that the keeping of this Talent of sound words and Doctrine doth herein <hi>differ</hi> from <note place="margin">4. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> must be imployed.</note> the keeping of such things as men commit to our trust; these may not he used, but onely kept, without imbezeling, till they be called for; this (as all Gods graees and gifts) must be used and imployed to such ends as God hath appointed, and to his glory, and good of Soules, and so must be returned with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, so that the not imployment and not improvement of the same makes men more guilty, <hi>Math.</hi> 25. 25.—30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Another Reason</hi> why this Doctrine is carefully to be kept is, because (as it is a matter of trust, so) <hi>it is a good and worthy</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> It is a good and worthy</hi> thing. And that 1. <hi>In regard of Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>thing,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 14. And worthy it is in divers respects. <hi>First,</hi> in regard of <hi>Matter,</hi> as containing the deepest mysteries, yea, revealing in Christ Crucified▪ truely taught, the deepest coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels <note place="margin">The vvisedome of God, and Christ crucified.</note> and wisedome of God, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 23. as being also the Doctrine of Salvation, <hi>Rom,</hi> 1. 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of the <hi>Author</hi> The eternall God and Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st▪ who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s both the <hi>Object</hi> of our wisedome (in whom, or in whose <note place="margin">2. Of Author, God and Christ.</note> Gospel and mystery of it, <hi>are hid all treasures of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sedome, and knowledge</hi> Colos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. 3) and the <hi>Author</hi> and worker of it in us, by the Gospel faithfully dispensed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>End</hi> of such Doctrine and use of it is, <hi>to make men wise to Salvation;</hi> being therefore ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed the Doctrine or Word <note place="margin">3. Of End, <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> of life, and the <hi>power of God to Salvation,</hi> Rom. 1. 16. yea, also to be a <hi>Rule</hi> to us least any beguile us with entising words, <hi>Colos.</hi> 2. 3. with 4. 8. So in regard of other particular effects, <note place="margin">And other divine effects.</note> this Law or Doctrine of the Lord restores <hi>or converts Soules—makes wise the simple—rejoyceth the heart—enlightens the eyes, &amp;c.</hi> Psal. 19 7. 8.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If <hi>compared with other things,</hi> which men account excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and <hi>worthy,</hi> their greatest care, pains and study, all the best <note place="margin">4. Better. <hi>being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red. then the best thing▪ on earth.</hi>
               </note> of them, are nothing to this Heavenly Doctrine; which is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:205727:18"/>
               <hi>more to be desired then Gold, yea, then much fine Gold, then thousands of Gold and Silver,</hi> Psal. 19. 10. and 119. 72. So Prov 3. 13. 14. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 16. 17. 18. <hi>All the things thou canst desire are not to be compared to her, i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Wisedome▪ &amp;c. Seeing such Heavenly Doctrine (rightly embraced) is so very precious, how shall we be able to answer it if we he unfaithfull <hi>Keepers</hi> of it? if we dispence it not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, if we corrupt and adulterate it by the mixture of our own wisedom and devises?</p>
            <p>Leaving other Reasons which might be urged by way of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (of which a touch hereafter) we will hasten to the <hi>Ʋse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vse.</hi> And <hi>first</hi> It may well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e wondred at (after such an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse charge given by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and to the Pastors of the Church) there should be any found of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o hard and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse <note place="margin"> 3. Ʋse. Here's matter of <hi>wonder,</hi> to see ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent vvith this Doctrine.</note> a fore-head, so impudent, so pertinacious, that yeelds not to the weight of these Heavenly Word, that is not subdued by these hammers, and crushed with these thunderbolts? That any should be so impiously wicked and blind, and should so de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in wayes of errour, as not to be content wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h that onely Rule of Faith, which anciently, (in the Scriptures, and by <hi>Paul)</hi> was once delivered in a forme of whole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome words to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and to the Church, and accordingly accepted; but should dayly seek one new thing after another, and continually long and endeavour to be <hi>adding</hi> some new and other thing to Religion, to <hi>change</hi> and take <hi>away</hi> at their pleasure.</p>
            <p>Thus wonders an ancient writer, even in that little Book against Heresies, which is so much magnified by the Popish <note place="margin">Vincent. Leri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens. lib. contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>reses. cap. 26.</note> sort, as if it made so much for them, and against us, whom alone they would have to be <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but he writing so long agoe (as dying under the Emperours <hi>Theodosius</hi> and <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian)</hi> did rather touch some <hi>Antichristian</hi> errors, as were then and formerly in the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d; and more fully Prophesie of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of the Romish Church, and the impud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt and shame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse errors of the same, as will now appear, if we consider how faulty, Papists especially, are this way, whose Church (if a <note place="margin">Of Confutation. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Especially of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Popish Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isb Churc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hich corrupts this</hi> Doctrine <hi>as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aithfull</hi> Keeper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f it.</note> Church) may (from what hath been said) be judged, and justly charged to be an unfaith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ull Keeper of Gods sacred truth, or of this <hi>Depositum,</hi> or matter of trust and charge committed to the Pastors of the Church, whilest they at pleasure <hi>detract corrupt,</hi> and <hi>change,</hi> and also <hi>adde</hi> to the Rule of Faith, contained in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:205727:18"/> the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> in the <hi>Apostles Creed,</hi> yea, and in the Faith of their <hi>Fathers,</hi> the ancient Romans.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Ground of Religion,</hi> namely, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of God; <hi>How are they k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pt?</hi> This appears, <hi>first</hi> by their <hi>adding</hi> the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphall</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> In the Ground of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> the</hi> Scriptures. 1 <hi>By</hi> adding. 2. <hi>By equalling</hi> Tradition<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. by <hi>corrupt Translation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>▪</hi>
               </note> Scriptures as equally authenticall. <hi>Secondly.</hi> By <hi>equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> their own <hi>Traditions</hi> to the Scripture. <hi>Thirdly▪</hi> By thrusting their <hi>Latine Translation</hi> upon the Church as authenticall, by which they overthrow the Text, even in the Fundamentall points of it: as if it were but that one place, there needed no more, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 15. which is the Foundation of the Faith of the Church in all ages, since the first revealing of Christ to the end of the World, Reading <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that is the Woman, (and they mean it of the blessed Virgin <hi>Mary)</hi> for <hi>it,</hi> the Seed of the Woman, <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> who is promised to bruise the Head▪ or Power of the Serpent, the Devill. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> By admitting no <note place="margin">4. <hi>By fastning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their own sence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the same.</hi>
               </note> sence of Scripture, but their own. Now▪ what Doctrine may not thus he defended? even that of <hi>Devils,</hi> which accordingly they doe defend, as 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1. 2. 3. Whether you take the words in the common acception of most or all Divines, of such Doctrines there mentioned, <hi>forbidding to Marry</hi> and <hi>commanding to abstain from meals,</hi> which are taught by the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, as <hi>Author</hi> of them or, as Master <hi>Mede</hi> takes them, for the Doctrine of Heathenish Daemons, which then were, and now are (under new Notions) no other then Devils, who get them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves worshipped under the names of Saints, Angels, Popes, and Breaden God▪ &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For <hi>the Forme of wholsome words,</hi> or Summe of Religion, which commonly we reduce to the <hi>Apostles Creed, Sacraments,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>In the</hi> forme <hi>of wholsome words.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Commandements, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Discipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Creed.</hi> 1. They overthrow, and in effect, deny <note place="margin">
                  <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> 1. In the Creed. 1. <hi>Overthrowing some</hi> Articles <hi>of it.</hi>
               </note> many particular Articles of it. I shall give but this one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance. We beleeve in <hi>Iesus Christ, born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>perfect God and perfect Man:</hi> so the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and <hi>Nicene Creed</hi> and other ancient Creeds, which tell us, that all the proprieties of the humane nature doe remain, as tangi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, locality, &amp;c. Now They overthrow by necessary conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence this Foundation of Faith, by teaching that Christs bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is truely and locally in the Sacrament, and in each severall Host or Wafer, distinct according to all the Members of it, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:205727:19"/> that in many places at once, and yet without taking up or fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any place, and not to be seen, felt, or tasted, &amp;c. and so in other Articles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They overthrow the <hi>scope</hi> of all whilest they deny par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <note place="margin">2. <hi>And the</hi> scope <hi>of it.</hi>
               </note> Faith application, and assurance.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They thrust in and adde twelve (or moe) new Articles of Faith, not conclusions from Principles in Scripture, but against <note place="margin">1. Adding <hi>new</hi> Articles <hi>to it.</hi>
               </note> the same; as are all (at least most) of the Points of difference between us and them; as appears by their Councels of <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran, Constance,</hi> and <hi>Trent:</hi> Unto which Articles they sweare such as enter into Orders: that is, sweare them to violate the Faith, once, and but once, delivered to the Saints, and which they should keep inviolably.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the <hi>Sacraments;</hi> They have taken away the <hi>Cup,</hi> in the Lords Supper, and <hi>added five</hi> of their own making, <note place="margin">2. In the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For the <hi>ten Commandements,</hi> they have taken away (out of all their Books or Missals) the second against their <hi>Images.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. In the ten Commandements</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. For <hi>Prayer;</hi> They add to the <hi>Object</hi> of it, persons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased, and make it onely a lip-labour. <note place="margin">4. In Prayer.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. And <hi>for Discipline and Government,</hi> they have added a <note place="margin">5. In Discipline.</note> new <hi>Head,</hi> the Pope, giving him a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ive authority, and not onely the power of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> The Canons of Scripture are not followed by them: nor other Canons of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Counsels, as not that which the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> used, called <hi>Codex Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m,</hi> containing the Canons of many ancient Councels, (in number, 165 Canons.) But what speak I of them, which yet shewes how little they regard what they so much pretended, <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Faith of the ancient Romans,</hi> of which yet they so <hi>brdg.</hi> Where is that better seen then in <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistle to the <note place="margin">3. In the saith of the Ancient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans.</note>
               <hi>Romans?</hi> of which Epistle it is truely said by some, that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing written <hi>ad Romanos,</hi> or <hi>to</hi> the Romans, is now <hi>Epistola Pauli in nunc Romanos; Pauls</hi> Epistle against the present <hi>Romans:</hi>
               <note place="margin">As appears by comparing their present Doctrine vvith <hi>Pauls Epistle</hi> to the Romans.</note> so cunningly hath <hi>Satan</hi> cheated them of the truth, and playd fast and loose with them, and such goodly and faithfull keepers of the truth they have shewed themselves to be, though they vainly conceit, they hold the truth fast still.</p>
            <p>This will appear to any indifferent eye, yea, to their own eyes, If they would not wilfully shut them, and say, they will
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:205727:19"/> not see, if we compare the Faith of both in some particulars. <note place="margin">Divers Distances▪</note> As <hi>first,</hi> concerning the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> of which <hi>Paul</hi> Writes honourably, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 4. But they call it a Book of Heresie, a dead Letter, Inky Divinity, &amp;c. <hi>Secondly,</hi> so concerning the <hi>Law,</hi> which they will not have impossible to us, though <hi>Paul</hi> makes it so, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Neither will they, have <hi>Concupiscence</hi> to be sinne, though <hi>Paul</hi> make it so, <hi>Row.</hi> 7. 7. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> And for the <hi>Gospel;</hi> he, <hi>first,</hi> contrary to them, teacheth <hi>Justification by Faith in Christ, and not by Works,</hi> Rom. 3. 4. 5. 6. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Assurance of <hi>Salvation,</hi> Rom. 8. 16. Thirdly, <hi>Eternall life</hi> to be Gods free gift, and not Merit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. last, and <hi>afflictions</hi> not to be worthy of the glory to be revealed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 18. Fourthly, <hi>Prayer</hi> onely to him in whom we may beleeve, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 14. Fifthly▪ <hi>Whatsoever is not of Faith, to be sinne,</hi> Rom. 14. last vers. which overthrows generally all <hi>Traditions.</hi> Sixtly, <hi>Subjection to secular Powers</hi> of all sorts of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1, from which they pleade im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity, for their Clergy.</p>
            <p>See then how they have kept the Faith of their forefathers. And though they succeed in place, so doth darknesse, light.</p>
            <p>Neither can it help them to plead Gods promise of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and of preservation made to his Church, when apparantly there is such difference▪ in their Faith, and the true ancient Faith of the Church, even that of <hi>Rome</hi> once. And if the times and first beginnings be not so apparant when such de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and errors crept in among them; shall they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be denied? Is not an old mans head gray, though the very first times of the change of colour were not observed?</p>
            <p n="2">2. The like Use of <hi>Confutation</hi> might be made of these so many <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w lights</hi> as blaze out like Comets in these our dayes, <note place="margin">2. Confutation of Sectaries.</note> by bringing them to the onely true and ancient light of Gods Word. But I deferre this till afterwards.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Onely what hath been said, serves also <hi>to the justifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Doctrine of our Church,</hi> against the older false lights <note place="margin"> 3. Ʋse.To justifie our Doctrine.</note> of <hi>Papists,</hi> and new lights of <hi>Sectarie,</hi> seeing we retaine the Scriptures without adding o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> altering, and teach the same, and no other Doctrine then that taught from the beginning of the Church, <hi>Gen,</hi> 3. 15. on which the Church then was grounded, and is now still built. So that it is a false Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge▪ that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:205727:20"/> is new; Which was <hi>first,</hi> long <hi>before Popery</hi> sprang up and consequently before <hi>Luthers</hi> Reformation or any since. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Under <hi>Popery,</hi> though oppressed by Popery; whose very oppressions and persecutions, then bare witnesse so farre to the truth. In which regard, by Gods wise and mercifull Providence, we came out (or rather were fired out) from amongst them, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="4">4. We might <hi>hence</hi> direct you how to <hi>judge of the truth,</hi> now a dayes, and of the falsehood of <hi>Doctrines</hi> which arise by <note place="margin">4. Of triall of Doctrine.</note> this onely Rule, Platforme and <hi>Doctrine</hi> committed to us, &amp;c. But of this more hereafter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. But we will rather conclude this Charge here given, with <hi>Exhortation</hi> to all as it concernes, and may be expe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5. Exhortation</hi> to keep the Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme of sound Doctrine.</note> from them especially <hi>Ministers</hi> of the Word, lawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>led, to shew their care, diligence and faithfulnesse in keeping the purity of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> as they have it from <hi>Paul,</hi> and other Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of holy Writ.</p>
            <p>To which end, <hi>first, As Platforms and Models of Divinity</hi> are needfull, (which must be onely according to Scripture, which is of prime authority and the onely Fundamentall Rule of Faith, as is shewed formerly;) so, care must be had to discharge our trust, in, and by a fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hfull ke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ping of the same. <note place="margin">Page 10.</note> This may be one <hi>Motive,</hi> added to the former Reasons, that <note place="margin">1. VVith one strong <hi>Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ive</hi> more thereunto.</note> according to thy faithfulnesse to God, will his faithfulne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se be to thee in such things as thou hast committed to his trust. And hast thou committed nothing to Gods keeping? or shalt thou never have need so to doe? <hi>Consider,</hi> Thou hast a precious <note place="margin">VVhich is, That as vve keep it, vve may expect God vvill keep that <hi>which</hi> vve have, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted unto him</note> soule and life, which undergoes a number of hazards, through the malice of Satan and Persecuters, through thine own weaknesse, yea, falsenesse of heart, and other wayes▪ now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse thou endeavour, at least to keep what God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to thee, how canst thou with comfort, whilest <hi>thou suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferest</hi> (though according to the will of God) <hi>commit the keeping of thy Soule to him</hi> (in well-doing) <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unto a faithfull Creator and Keeper?</hi> 1 Pet. 4 19. How, in thy suffer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngs, canst thou say with <hi>Paul—I am not ashamed: for I know whom I have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved</hi> (or trusted) <hi>and I am perswaded that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e is able</hi> (as well as willing) <hi>to keep that which I have committed to him against that day,</hi> z Tim. 1. 12. He might with confidence and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:205727:20"/> hope when he came to dye, so say and <hi>expect a Crown of Righteousnesse laid up,</hi> (and so kept) <hi>for him;</hi> inasmuch as he could also truely say, <hi>I have fought a good fight, I have finished my course, I have kept the Faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 4. 7. 8. He kept that constantly and faithfully, which he would have <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy,</hi> and us his successors, likewise to keep; who may also expect a like Crowne at that day.</p>
            <p>Thou hast also thy good name, goods, life, wife, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, all which stand need of Gods Keeping, and who hath undertaken the charge of them, especially after thy decease; If thou wouldest have him to he faithfull to thee in these, be thou true and faithfull to him in this.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But <hi>how</hi> must it be kept? The <hi>Direction</hi> follows in the next words, <hi>Avoyding prophane—vain-bablings, And oppositions</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>▪</hi> And so <hi>we</hi> come to the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of the <hi>Tex,</hi> vvhich i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>A Direction to the Way and Means of keeping sound<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Doctrine.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>of Science, falsely so called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Word are both <hi>part</hi> of the charge given to <hi>Timothy,</hi> and they <hi>direct</hi> to the manner and means of keeping the same. How then and by what means▪ may the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ty of <hi>Doctrine</hi> be preserved? One principall way and means is made here to consist in the avoyding of two things. <hi>First, Vaine babling. Secondly, oppositions</hi> of pretended <hi>Science</hi> and knowledge. So we have the like preservative and means di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected unto, in the second Epistle, Chap. 2. 14. 15. 16,—23. <hi>Charge them, before the Lord that they strive not about Words.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Which is to avoyd false</hi> Doctrine.</note>
               <hi>to no profit, but to the subverting of the hearers—but shun pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and vain bablings, for they will increase to more ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse—but foolish and unlearned questions avoyd, knowing that they doe gender strifes.</hi> Where we also see the great evills of such vain bablings and oppositions of Science; they are not onely <hi>unprofitable,</hi> but tend to the begetting and gendring of <hi>strifes</hi> and <hi>contentions▪</hi> to the <hi>subverting of the Faith of the hearers,</hi> to the encrease of <hi>ungodlinesse and prophanesse</hi> in their lives; and as <hi>Paul</hi> in the next words to my Text, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. <hi>Such professing of Science, causeth an erring in them concerning the Faith,</hi> which may be so many <hi>Dissuasives</hi> from such prosession and practise and <hi>motives</hi> for the avoyding of them.</p>
            <p>But my purpose is not to insist thereon, or to be large on these, or the following words; but applying my selfe more specially, to these our present times (having said enough
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:205727:21"/> against <hi>Popery</hi> before) to adde and conclude this Text with this one Generall <hi>Doctrine;</hi> That,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true Ministers of Jesus Christ, as they desire, and are bound to keep faithfully his Doctrine in purity, so they ought</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctrine. Ministers ought to avoyd prophane and vain-bablings, and all opposition made against the Truth.</note>
               <hi>earefully to avoid pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phane and vain bablings, and all opposition of their own, and others Wit, and pretended Knowledge, against the ancient truths of God, delivered to them in the Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where I n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed not tell you, what it is to <hi>avoyd</hi> these: It implyeth a shunning to teach and vent such things our selves, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. What i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to avoyd</hi> See also Rom 16. 17. 18. 2. Tim. 3. 3. 4.</note> a rejecting of them, or not hearkning to them, when taught by others, yea, <hi>a stopping of the monthes of such,</hi> Tit 1. 9.—11. if not a rejecting of their Persons, <hi>after the first and second admonition,</hi> Tit. 3. 9. 10. howsoever, as it especially concernes hearers, whose Faith hereby is indangered, it implyeth a shunning of the company of such, and a stopping of the ears against their Charmes. That which will chiefly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern us all to know, is rather, <hi>What</hi> is to be avoyded. Now these are reduced to two heads here. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. What is to be avoyded.</hi> Two things.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The first is, <hi>prophane—vain bablings.</hi> Elsewhere a <hi>stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving about Words: foolish questions and Genealogies, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and strivings about the Law, as being unprofitable, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Bablings and false Teachers.</note>
               <hi>vain,</hi> Tit. 3. 9. <hi>Jewish Fables, and commandements of men, unto which, no heed is to be given as turning (men) from the truth,</hi> Tit. 1. 14 and 11 <hi>a teaching things which ought not</hi> (be taught.) For as <hi>Paul</hi> there <hi>ver.</hi> 10. tells Tiths, <hi>There are many unruly, and vain talkers, and deceivers, whose mouthes must be stopped.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this evill or babling, hath two <hi>epithites</hi> given it; the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Which have two</hi> Epe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes <hi>or three.</hi>
               </note> one is included in the Word, <hi>kenophonias</hi> namely <hi>vaine</hi> or <hi>empty;</hi> which yet some of the ancients Reade, <hi>kainophonias,</hi> or <hi>New,</hi> or <hi>Novelites</hi> of Words. The other, <hi>bebeelous, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane,</hi> And both of them in the Plural; as if all the babling; and talking (I cannot call it Preaching) of these deceivers, were such both vain and prophane. I shall but touch upon them briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Vaine;</hi> which, being wrapped up in the Word here used, <note place="margin">They are, 1. Vaine 1. Empty</note> Notes first <hi>Empty,</hi> and implyeth, <hi>an emptinesse of Words,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Words without matter, substance, solidity and soundnesse of truth: or ground of Scripture empty Words, like them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, <hi>Clouds without Water, carried about of Winds. Trees,</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:205727:21"/>
               <hi>whose Fruit Withereth, without Fruit,</hi> Jude vers. 12. <hi>Wells with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Water,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 17.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Vaine</hi> or <hi>frustrate,</hi> which attain not their end, or not the true end of Teaching, as bringing neither glory to God, nor <note place="margin">2. Frustrate and wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out profit or go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fruit to any. Bringing neither▪</note> profit to the hearers, but onely a subverting of their Faith, and a turning them from the truth. Such were the false Prophets of old, of whom God speaketh, <hi>I have not sent these Prophets, yet</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Glory to God.</note>
               <hi>they ran; I have not spoken to them, yet they Prophesied. But</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Good and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version to other▪</note>
               <hi>if they had stood in my Counsell, and had caused my People to beare my Words, then they should have turned them from their evill way, and from the evill of their doings—</hi>but (now) <hi>they cause my people to erre by their lies and lightnesse; yet I sent them not, nor commanded them; therefore they shall not profit this people at all saith the Lord,</hi> Jeremy 23. 21. 22.—32. The like is, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 6.—8. 9.—23 And such false Teachers were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told to be among us. And surely, if we may judge of such by their running without being sent, and by the fruitlessenesse of their bablings, whereby, though we see many <hi>perverted by them, and following their pernicious wayes,</hi> yet where shall we see one, in these our dayes (in which such Prophets, (at least with us in <hi>England)</hi> abound more then ever in any age for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) <hi>Converted</hi> truely unto God, or turned from their evill way, or from the evill of their doings? I say if such Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conversion be a signe of such vain bablers; we may truely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, they are either these amongst us now, in our Cities, Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons, armies; or there are no such men any where else in the World (of Christians) to be found. We see so little fruit of this nature among them, (I meane especially, <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, Socineans, Familists, Seekers,</hi> and other high-flowne <note place="margin">VVho are perv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them.</note>
               <hi>Sectaries,</hi> who will be above all Ordinances of God) that where there were some, either true beginnings, or otherwise great shews of grace and holinesse, there is nothing, or very little to be seen, but loosenesse of life, carelesse walking with God, and an inclination, at least, if not some degrees of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanesse both of life and opinion. Of which anon.</p>
            <p>Such Teachers, <hi>Paul</hi> calls, <hi>Deceivers, Vaine-talkers,</hi> and <hi>unruly,</hi> or under no order, or Government, keeping no ranke, every one a Master, Teacher, or Commander.</p>
            <p>Now these, and such as these, are to be avoyded, if we
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:205727:22"/> would keep that good thing committed to our charge, and as we love our Soules. These are not to be regarded, because they can talk much, or long, and utter words and Phrases beyond your reach, or because of faire shews, great braggs, large promises of Liberty or Profession of deep and hidden Science and Knowledge above others. No we know that <hi>empty Vessels</hi> make the greatest sound, but affoard little or no good liquor. And <hi>Wells</hi> promise refreshing and water to the thirsty, yet being empty, are dry and barren, and send away empty the weary Traveller. <hi>Such use swelling words of vanity, and so allure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> those</hi> (novice Christians) who were <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> again intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by them with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llutions.</note> weak in Knowledge, Faith, and Practise: yea▪ and those <hi>that were clean escaped from them, true beleevers,</hi> and such as otherwise belonging to God, he may, for a time suffer to be shaken <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eodate.</note> by their temptations, but not finally to be overthrown; or rather, <hi>those</hi> who by professing the Gospel, had taken the true way of saving themselves, but are now by them perverted, live in errour, <hi>and again intangled with the pollut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons of the World, and overcome,</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 1. 2. 3. with 17. 18. 19. 20. And indeed, who prate more of Religion then such Scyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists, as, despising found learning whether humane or divine, and sleighting Gods Publique Ordinances, <hi>creep into houses, &amp;c.</hi> their manners are fully described, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>▪ <hi>having a forme of Godlinesse, but denying the power thereof, from such,</hi> saith the Apostle <hi>turne away—these are they,</hi> who as <hi>Jannes and Jambres</hi> withstood <hi>Moses</hi> (by Miracles, Rods, and Serpents, which were not truely so, but onely in shew, yet enough to harden <hi>Pharaoh)</hi> so do these <hi>resist the truth,</hi> vers. 8. who must therefore be resisted rejected, turned from, and avoyded. What sound or solid Doctrine can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from such, who have no grounds of Learning them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, as not humane, so not out of Gods word and Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which they sleight, as well as humane Learning; and under pretence of more immediate Teaching, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y out of Studied Sermons, &amp;c. To conclude this first Epithite, by hearkening to such vaine-babling you will finde your selves in the end, left empty, and frustrate of that you vainely and in curiosity, seek or expect from them: whereas <hi>Pauls</hi> Preaching (and theirs who follow his steps) was of another
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:205727:22"/> nature, <hi>and not in vain,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. to. that is, neither unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Church, nor to himselfe, as are the <hi>vain Visions</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> of such upstart Prophets, who as they bring no profit to the People, so nothing but Judgement, in the end upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. <hi>Therefore, thus saith the Lord—mine hand shall be upon the Prophets that see vanity—They shall not be in the Assembly, (socret or counsel) of my People,</hi> (as having allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to speak in Publique Assemblies, as true Prophets had, <hi>Jeremy</hi> 26. 7.) <hi>neither shall they be Writed in the Writing of the house of Israel, &amp;c.</hi> they shall be of no reckoning nor account with me, nor so much as members of the sacred Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (for all their profession of holinesse and Saint-ship) who were all numbred and in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olled▪ <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi> 20. 12 but rooted out of the holy Land▪ yea <hi>of the World</hi> Ezek. 13. 9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But, as it is said, some of the ancients <hi>(Augustine,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n=""/>
               <hi>Chrysostome, Ambrose</hi> and <hi>Basil,</hi> wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h <hi>Vincentius Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inensis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">They are new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> novel opinion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. As some dead<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> word. Novelties o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> word Boza i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot.</note> and the Vulgar Latine) roade these Words, not <hi>keno—</hi>but <hi>kainoph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nias,</hi> not vain-babling, but <hi>new<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>sse of Words,</hi> and of Language; and this is also very offensive and dangerous, and commonly tends to the detriment and corrupting of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>some Doctrine▪ and argues much lightnesse and vanity of mind and wit. It is to be observed, how some now adayes especially, doe wonderfully please themselves▪ in the use of uncouth words, and innovation of Words and Phrases, with new Formes of Speech, with a gibberish and je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gon Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, such as the Scripture own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not, and which▪ men true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wise, and spirituall, use not, yea, understand not; seeing <note place="margin">Innovation of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> VVords and Phr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ses dangerous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ch.</note> under such strange<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and affected Language, they have cause to suspect some deceit is hid, and a quite contrary meaning to that which is pretended by them. As to <hi>unknow sinne,</hi> which in a charitable construction, may i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ply, to look on sin a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a stranger an enemy, and to have no more to doe with it: and so being urged, they will tell you, that is their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: yet in very deed their meaning is, a not being touched with any sence, remorse, or conscience, for sinne committed; as supposing themselves in such an estate now, as <hi>Adam</hi> was in before the Fall, who knew experementally, onely good, and not evill. I have had experience of this, and the like <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be suspecte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of dec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>▪</note>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:205727:23"/> juggling of some Familists? as Master <hi>Calvin</hi> mentions the <note place="margin">And to be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</note> like in the <hi>Lebertines</hi> in his time.</p>
            <p>Now these Words so read belong to such Innovators of Words and Phrases and bid us beware of such prophane No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties, <hi>least any spoile us through such vain deceit.</hi> And so <note place="margin">Coloss. 2. 8.</note> bidding us avoyd Novelties, whether of words, or of things and Doctrine, he shews what, on the contrary we should follow, namely, ancient Truths, and Scripture Language; for if Noveltie be prophane antiquity, (ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ording to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) is sacred Its not to yeild, so much as in a Letter, to such as we have cause to suspect.</p>
            <p>Let this also teach us all not to stumble at the (supposed) <note place="margin">VVhereas we are not to stumble at the seeming homeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of Scripture-Phrases.</note> meanenesse, and (as we in our shallownesse are ready to think) at the low Phrases and expressions of the Scripture-stile, or lownesse of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of Christ crucified, and of his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, &amp;c. Affect not in your selves, or others, high No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, unusuall expressions, to make you onely admire what ye understand not, or to take them the rather to savour of more spiritualnesse; when, in truth, there is nothing in such affected suttleties of words, but deceit. Keep we rather <hi>Pauls</hi> Forme of wholesome words; and let us learne to be <hi>joyned, not onely in the same mind and judgement, according to Gods Word, but also to speak the same things,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 10.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>second Epithite</hi> in the Text▪ is <hi>Prophane:</hi> So 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 16. And what is <hi>Prophane?</hi> that which hath <note place="margin">3. Prophane. <hi>VVhat is Prophane.</hi>
               </note> nothing sacred, nothing truely religious in it, as being strange and farre from the wholesome Truths taught in the Word and Church of God, which is his <hi>Temple;</hi> new and unheard of <hi>opinions</hi> obtruded upon Gods People, and as it were <hi>New and other Gods which we have not known,</hi> as <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 2. as <note place="margin">Vincent Lerin. cap. 15.</note> the old Testament so calls them in an Allegoricall way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause such Hereticks observe and stick to their own opinions, and honour them, as the Heathen observed their gods, or <note place="margin">Hyperius, in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> these bablings are <hi>Prophane,</hi> as being impure, polluted, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Now, This prophanenesse may referre either to prophane <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prophane, may be referred either to</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prophane Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons▪ <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wo so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> and carnall men, to men of prophane Spirits: or to such <hi>Doctrine</hi> as tends to prophanesse.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:205727:23"/> 1. Of <hi>prophane and carnall men;</hi> who yet would be distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guished: Some, otherwise truely spirituall, may be called <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Comparatively▪ so, being otherwise, (though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake) y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in Crhist.</note> comparatively to such as are more Spirituall, and raysed: <hi>Babes in Christ,</hi> unto whom <hi>Paul could not speak as unto Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, but as unto carnall—as not able yet to bear</hi> (strong) <hi>meat, but to be fed with Milk. For</hi> (saith <hi>Paul) ye are ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> carnall;</hi> which he said because of envying, strife, and divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and factions among them, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. <hi>For which one saith, I am of Paul, and another, I am of Apollo, are ye not carnall?</hi> ver. 4. Whereas if they had eyes to discerne, they would find <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollo, Cephas</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> all to agree in one. But such commonly in yong beginners is their zeale to their own <note place="margin">These are often gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven to strife and contentions in an ignorant zeale <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their teachers.</note> more immediate Teachers by whom they have any whit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited, as that they envy the like or better parts of others, as disparaging such as whom they zealously (but not well) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, that they might exclude others. As <hi>Johns Disciples</hi> in zeale to him their Master, sought to lay envy on Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, <hi>John</hi> 3. 26. This blind zeal, in such, we may a while beare with, and pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty▪ but yet must take heed of it: It sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours too much of the flesh, of corruption, and of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. They contend prophanely about they know not what, as those two, who both zealous of <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> and his Reformation, contended the one with the other, the one under the Notion of a <hi>Lutheran,</hi> the other of a <hi>Martinist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Some again truely (if not wholly) carnall, naturall <note place="margin">2. Truely prophane, and servants of corruption.</note> and of prophane Spirits, as <hi>Poter</hi> speaks of them, speak <hi>great swelling words of vanity, and allure, through the lusts of the flesh, through much wantonnesse, those that were clean</hi> (or for a little, or a while) <hi>escaped from them who live in errour: whilo they promise them liberty, they themselves are the servants of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Framing the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and their opi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons accordingly.</note>
               <hi>corruption, &amp;c.</hi> 2 Pet. 2. 18. 19. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Such are they generally as are of unreformed lives them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and therefore can never have a constant sound judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Divine Truths, nor true and hearty love to it. These either bring sences and meanings of their own unto the Scripture, or prophanely suit, apply, and wrest Scripture to their own meanings, disposition, and affection, thereby to justifie, if they could, their own leud practises, opinions, and wayes: as being <hi>covetous,</hi> they wrest that Scripture, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 8.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:205727:24"/>
               <hi>If any provide not for his own—he is worse then an Infidel:</hi> and for deferring Repentance abuse other Scriptures. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever, for want of true and sound love to <hi>true Doctrine,</hi> they are justly given up to beleeve (and to teach) lyes, 2 <hi>Thess.</hi> 2. 10. 11. <hi>Jude Ver.</hi> 10.<hi>—What they know naturally as brute beast, in those things they corrupt themselves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But for us, It teacheth us <hi>first,</hi> to desare especially to <hi>heare such as are most conscientious themselves;</hi> and endeavour a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity <note place="margin">Ʋse.1.To heare holy teachers.</note> of life to the pure word which they teach. and who Russian-like, conforme not to the fashions of the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 1. 2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> And for our <hi>own practise, to study holinesse of life,</hi> and labour to live according to that <hi>Doctrine</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. To study holinesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> life in our selves.</note> which is according to godlinesse; and according to that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of knowledge, though it be but small, which we have: for we have a promise, <hi>John</hi> 7. 17. <hi>If any man will doe his will,</hi> (that good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 2.) <hi>he shall know of the Doctrine, whether it be of God—</hi>that is, he that makes conscience to doe what he knows, shall know more, yea, and more certainly, and be assured of what he knows, and so shall be kept from an <hi>ignorant doting about questions and strifes of words—perverse disputings of men of</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 6. 3. 4. 5.</note>
               <hi>corrupt</hi> (and prophane) <hi>minds, and destitute of the truth, &amp;c.</hi> Otherwise, God will extinguish that little light men have, and give up to errour delusion and a reprobate mind; so pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishing prophanesse of heart and life, by, and with a corrupt judgement, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 28.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Prophane babling▪</hi> relates to <hi>such Doctrine as tends to Prophanesse,</hi> and opens a way to licenciousnesse of life, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Or to prophane</hi> Doctrine.</note> opinion; whereby the name of God, and his Doctrine is blasphemed; as to <hi>teach▪</hi> that <hi>Servants,</hi> being converts and Christians owe not that honour to their own Masters (as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly) who either as yet beleeve not, or as are beleeving: and so may despise them, because they are <hi>Brethren,</hi> and in that relation <hi>equals.</hi> This is no part of that <hi>Doctrine which is according to godlinesse,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 1. 2. with 3. but argues pride and ignorance, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. Such are the Doctrines of those that make all, 1. <hi>Times and Dayes alike,</hi> as denying <hi>the mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Such</hi> Doctrines <hi>as make alike holy.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>of the Christian Sabbath,</hi> and making each day alike; so hiding their eyes from the Lords Sabbaths, whereby▪ he is <note place="margin">1. All times and dayes.</note>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:205727:24"/>
               <hi>prophaned</hi> among them. 2. That make all <hi>Person<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> alike, (especially of their own Profession;) <hi>all the Congregation to</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ad Persons,</hi> Numb. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f all alike, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> gifted, might co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er to God in the holy calling of the Ministers.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>be holy, or Saints</hi> (as in the Originall) fit to offer their own sacrifice, and to thrust into the Priests Office; and as for <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> the <hi>Saint of God</hi> whom God had <hi>chosen and called, they</hi> are charged <hi>to take too much upon them, and to lift up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves above the Congregation of the Lord.</hi> But the Lord presently shewed with a witnesse, who were <hi>his,</hi> and who <hi>holy and Saints</hi> and called to come neer unto him, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 1. 2. 3. 4. 5 &amp;c. These also are the Priests, that put <hi>no difference between the holy and prophane, neither shew diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the unclean and clean—</hi>Ezek. 22. 26. 3. That make all <hi>things</hi> alike, <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Gods Law, and prophaning his</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 3. <hi>All</hi> things.</note>
               <hi>holy things, and the name of the Lord of Hosts, in that</hi> (with the Priests and People of old) <hi>they▪</hi> in effect, and by their practise, <hi>say, The Table of the Lord is polluted, and the fruit thereof, even his meat is contemptible,</hi> Malachy 1. 12. This <note place="margin">Pollating Gods Altar,</note> was spoken of the Altar and sacrifices offered thereon, which, as holy signes of Gods presence among them, were to be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as of the best, so from knowledge and Faith and with repentance and holy meditation, and so with reverence to Gods name.</p>
            <p>Now, looking on the Altar, as being much short of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that splendour which it had before the Captivity, and nos discerning aright the end and use of the Sacrifices; they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed offered them, but this they did▪ both remaining still in their sinnes, ignorance, impenitency and unbeleefe; and also <note place="margin">Sacrifices of old.</note> thinking any thing or Sacrifice good enough for God, though it were torn lame, and sick: and so by their contempt of the signes, they bewrayed a prophane conceit yea, and contempt, of all godlinesse and of God himselfe.</p>
            <p>And thus it is now with such, as not looking upon the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And new his</hi> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances.</note> Ministery or Doctrine, or on the Sacraments, <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> of God, and <hi>as</hi> having annexed to them, in the right use those of speciall and higher blessings then the signes and what is outward in them, can reach unto, count meanly of them, and as ordinary things. And so <hi>some</hi> presume to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take <note place="margin">VVord.</note> of them in their sinnes without due reverence and prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of heart, and so offer blind and lame Sacrifices; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:205727:25"/> prophaner sort. Some look on the <hi>Sacraments</hi> onely as bare <note place="margin">Sacraments.</note> signes, as the <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> and on the <hi>Word</hi> so▪ as that any common (and so farre prophane) man may at his own hand <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And</hi> Table.</note> take up the Ministery of it. <hi>Otkers</hi> admire themselves, as being above all Ordinances, which accordingly they debase; as expecting good from God some other and higher way. And <hi>lastly, some</hi> look upon the holy Sacrament and Tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of the Lord, as contemptible prophane and polluted (at least) to them, if they should partake of it with any such, as they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count not Saints, and true converts in the strictest sence. Though it be most true, that none but such partake savingly thereof: yet whether it simply be a polluting of that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance and Table, if such be admitted as professe Faith, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and a serious desire and purpose to renue their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and thus to seale it, (being otherwise assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and told of the danger of unworthy Receiving) I leave it to further disquisition. But this by the way.</p>
            <p>Onely for <hi>conclusion</hi> of this Branch, it would be conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Whereas</hi> Paul <hi>and faithfull teachers maintain the</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse▪</hi>
               </note> that though by some, the best and holiest Teachers may be thought to be <hi>biblers</hi> for so <hi>Paul,</hi> by the prophane Heathen <hi>Athenians,</hi> was called and accounted, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 18. Yet such onely consent to, and trach wholesome words, <hi>even the words of our Lord Jesu Christ, and the Doctrine which is according to godlinesse,</hi> and which leads thereunto. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Titus▪</hi> and in him all faithfull Teachers, saying, <hi>This is a faithfull saying, and these things, I will that thou affirme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly, that they which have beleeved on God, might be carefull to maintain good works these things are good and profitable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to men. But avoyd foolish questions and strivings about the Law; for they are unprofitable and vain,</hi> Titus 3. 8. 9. and not onely <hi>vain</hi> but <hi>prophane,</hi> and tend to prophanesse; which <hi>Paul</hi> here would have us avoyd; and as elsewhere, <hi>shun;</hi> and that upon this ground; <hi>But shun prophane and vain bablings; for they will increase to more ungodlinesse,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 16. and at length, end in irreligion and Athei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me; as we see too palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in these our dayes. </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>second thing</hi> here to be avoyded is, <hi>Antithesi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or <note place="margin">2. The second thing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e avo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded, are Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>s of Science <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> falsely so called) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of New Ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note>
               <hi>opposition of Science</hi> falsely so called: or <hi>oppositions</hi> and <hi>gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayings of sinners,</hi> and their <hi>contradictions</hi> of Christ, and the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:205727:25"/> truths of the Gospel, which many use in a confidence or vain conceit of their own knowledge and wisedom, such as the proud <hi>Pharisees,</hi> who thought themselves the onely seeing and knowing men in their time, <hi>John</hi> 9. 40. 41. such as the <note place="margin">Which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>▪</note> old and new <hi>Gnosticks</hi> the <hi>Jesuets,</hi> who, like the Greeks of old account, all <hi>Barbarians</hi> to themselves, or like many now in these our dayes, who, under pretence of deeper and higher wisedome, new lights and discoveries, and (in a word,) of wisedome pretended to be taught them more immediately by the Spirit, and above the Word and Scriptures, or at least above common capacities, do seek, through their acute and crafty subtilties and wranglings, <hi>to oppose</hi> the holy truths of God, his ways and worship, advancing their own supposed wisedome and science, against the same, at least, equalling themselves (for gifts and authority from God to Preach, and Baptize) to the Apostle <hi>Peter,</hi> professing, (and it was professed by the Anabaptist <hi>T. L.)</hi> that he had as good ground and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <note place="margin">Anthaptists grounds—found false in preface.</note> from God, for that he undertook to doe and practise, as the Apostle <hi>Peter</hi> had for that which he did, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. So <note place="margin">They oppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves and their supposed Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> that now it seems, we must so farre admire, beleeve and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their Doctrine, and so farre honour the Spirit of God speaking <hi>to them▪ in them</hi> and <hi>by them,</hi> as not to offer <hi>to try</hi>
               <note place="margin">To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>▪</note>
               <hi>the Spirits</hi> (by which men speak) any longer by the Word &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Scriptures tell us of some whom it calls <hi>antilegon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n sayers</hi> of sound Doctrine, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1. 9. and <hi>antidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tithem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nous, such as oppose themselves,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 25. We, passing by other times, yea, and places, may look upon a Generation of men among our selves in these dayes of liberty, and take notice and see, what an <hi>high strain of knowledge</hi> some are come unto, and others are following hard after, &amp;c. who so farre advance their supposed knowledge by the Spirit, as that they <hi>oppose it</hi> to the crying down.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of <hi>many ancient and Fundamentall truths,</hi> under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of their <hi>new lights:</hi> calling and accounting the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Many Funda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> truths.</note> Teachers of Orthodox Doctrine, Priests of Antichrist, or of Baal; herein shewing themselves like the blasphemous Jews of old, who, <hi>filled with envy, spake against those things which were spoken by</hi> Paul. <hi>contradicting and blaspheming,</hi> Acts 13. 45.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:205727:26"/> 2. <hi>Of the Scriptures</hi> themselves, and their authority, in part at least, if not wholly. And this they doe whilest, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e holy Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b they make</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e VValdwins <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ile<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o oppose them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ves by contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion▪ The New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt to oppose the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. The whole, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se the Spirit, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Spirit▪ it.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They charge them with <hi>Contradictions</hi> (and so make the Scriptures oppose themselves) and with obscurities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They <hi>deny the Authority</hi> of the Old Testament, as of no binding power to them now: and so <hi>oppose</hi> the New and Old Testament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Yea, <hi>they deny the Scripture to be a Rule,</hi> touchstone, or stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of truth; and so <hi>oppose</hi> it to the Spirit and to their supposed spirituall revelations, as that they count it a straitning to the Spirit of God, and an indignity offered unto it, to bring it (and their supposed Inspirations) to the touchstone of the Scriptures. Of such small account are the Scriptures with them, as if they were a Rule onely of mens Invention, and not of Gods own Ordination; or as if they were not given by the Inspiration of the Spirit of God, and therefore not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes uniforme to the Spirit by which at first they were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. And thus doing, the difference will prove to be not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Scriptures and the Spirit of God, which agree well enough, and are ever like themselves; but between the Spirit of God, by which the Scriptures were given and their <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Spirit</hi> by which they speak and so <hi>oppose</hi> at once, both Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Spirit,</hi> and the <hi>Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Howsoever, they so farre oppose their own understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Scriptures, that, pretending they are dark, obscure, <note place="margin">4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y corrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pture by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>es.</note> misterious, and hidden, and the mistery wrapped up in the history, they must be unfolded by their <hi>allegorizing</hi> of them: so making them speak what they in their wisedome think they should <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eak, though it be non-sence: As if the darknesse were in the Scriptures, and not in themselves: Pride so <hi>blinds</hi> their eyes, that under pretence of running farre enough from the Letter, which they judge carnall and killing, they make it (by allegorizing) eccho to the found which is already in their <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> his co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rations vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the use of Scriptures Ordinances.</note> own cares, as one speaks, who knows them well enough.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Nay yet, looking upon their own wayes of holinesse, as higher then the Scriptures can bring them unto, they think the <hi>use of the Scriptures hath its period</hi> and time with men▪ beyond which it is uselesse, and improper to attend to it▪ <note place="margin">
                  <hi>5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ibid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 19. 18. &amp;c.</note> though formerly of use. So they interpret, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:205727:26"/>
               <hi>Esay</hi> 54. 13. <hi>Jeremy</hi> 31. 34. and 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 20. 21.—27. Which place the said Writer sufficiently vindicates.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Howsoever, some we have, as <hi>Walwin,</hi> and those of his stampe, That <hi>question the authority of Scripture,</hi> and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Satan</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. They <hi>questi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> VVal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> them.</hi>
               </note> delt with <hi>Eve</hi> by questioning<hi>—hath God said, &amp;c.</hi> so they with their Proselytes<hi>—how know you the Scriptures to be Gods Word. &amp;c.</hi> and at length flatly deny them any autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, so bringing in nothing but prophanesse, licentiousnesse, and at length, meer Atheisme, and so by a Popish but Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish policy, denuding them of all Religion, make them fit to <note place="margin">Vostius in loci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de Athelsmo.</note> receive, what new Impressions (like an empty Table-Book) they please, and so to win them sooner to themselves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They oppose their wisedome, not onely to overthrow the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but by a new kind of Levelling, they would <note place="margin">3. They <hi>oppose</hi> the vvisedom to c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>down</hi> Ordinance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> subject the <hi>Wisedom of God therein,</hi> and thereby manifested to the modell and scantling of their own fancy and foolish opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and conceits, under the name of <hi>Spirituall Revelations;</hi> whilest they, (accounting it seems Gods wisedome to be foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishnesse) mount themselves above all his <hi>Ordinances as of Preaching the Word</hi> (though it be the Preaching of Christ Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified) <hi>of Baptisme</hi> (that of Water, which they utterly deny) <hi>the Lords Supper,</hi> Church-fellowship and assembling.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And, (to give you it in the words of another) <hi>after they have a while served their turn of Christ Crucified, they sting</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Yea,</hi> to see <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Christ himselfe.</note>
               <hi>him away as an eliment as beggerly as any of those Ordinances which represent it, and under I know not what vanity, or pride</hi>
               <note place="margin">M. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>of Notion, cast that behind their back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, which</hi> Paul <hi>in his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing desired specially to know and manifest,</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 2.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Last of all, some are come to such an <hi>heigth,</hi> as to make themselves Christ and God, and to stile themselves, <hi>The</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Nay, to call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> make themselv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God, ibid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Lord of Hosts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Blasphemons Pride! This is indeed with a witnesse, to be <hi>Godded with God▪</hi> and <hi>Christed with Christ;</hi> which is a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>All this knowle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Science fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> called.</note> piece of the Doctrine of <hi>H. N. father of the Familists.</hi> What kind of Wisedome and Knowledge is this, that these New-Teachers have attained unto. May not the Apostle very well, and in a gentle tearme, name it, <hi>Science, falsely so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</hi> what is it indeed but folly, if not▪ fury and madnesse: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke that (but farre transcending) of the Pagan <hi>Romans,</hi> of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:205727:27"/> whom it is said, <hi>Professing themselves wise, they became fools,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (though <hi>ly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise mucb,)</hi>
               </note> Rom. 1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. so its here added in the next verse, (but I mean not to prosecute it) concerning the <hi>Science</hi> of these wise Masters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which some professing, have erred concerning the Faith.</hi> And <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> an erring concerning the Faith, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llons,</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tim. 6. 22.</note> what is this they professe, (or as some reade, promise?) but some new and unknown Doctrine, which they call the true Faith, and which none besides themselves understand, hid from ages, newly revealed to them, which their Disciples must learn in secret, and by stealth, and teach as privately, it being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely to a few to understand the secret of▪ such a Mystery: <note place="margin">Vincent. Lerin. contra hares. cap. 26.</note> And as one Praphrasing on those words, <hi>asketh</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">are not these the words of the Harlot, which calls Passengers which goe right on their way? <hi>Who so is simple, let him turn in hither, and as for him that wanteth understanding, shee saith to him, stolen waters are sweet, and bread</hi> (of secresies, or) <hi>eaten in</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 13. 14. 15. 16. 17. 18.</note>
                  <hi>secret is pleasant:</hi>
               </q> But what follows? <hi>But he knoweth not that the dead are there, and that her guests are in the depths of Hell.</hi> And who are these her guests? such, saith <hi>Paul,</hi> as with themselves, <hi>have erred concerning the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such high knowledge so promised and professed, is but errour and science misnamed or false. Such wisedom may soon be dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, <note place="margin">Verè falsum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men apud doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas haereticorum. ut ignoranna sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, &amp; caligo screni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>brae lumjuis ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>atione fucen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Vincent. Lerinens. ibid. <hi>Its no wisedome from alove.</hi> Iames 3. 13. 14. 15. 16. 17.</note> by that description which Saint <hi>James</hi> gives of the like; and from the <hi>Properties</hi> of that wisedome which is true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from above. Of the one, he saith there is no cause to glory in it, seeing it is but a <hi>lying against the truth, if men have bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter envying and strife in their hearts</hi> (as such Men as we speak of seldom want it.) <hi>This wisedom descendeth not from above, but is earthly, sensuall</hi> (or naturall) <hi>and devilish—But the wisedome that is from above is first pure, then penceable, gentle, and easie to be entreated, full of mercy and good fruits, without partiality</hi> (or wrangling: and last of all) <hi>without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither need we other <hi>argument to disswade</hi> from such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">And such erring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> arguments enough against is.</note> Profession of Science (which some make shew of, as if they, and they onely, by their new light, knew the whole mind of God) then this, that commonly such as so professe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise most, soonest erre or goe astray concerning the Faith, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. that is, they (and their admirers and followers) misse
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:205727:27"/> of the maine scope and marke of the Gospel; which is he sleight errour in Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igion, but is an overthrowing of the Fundamentals thereof, which they hold no longer, and that perniciously to the subverting and overthrowing of their own Faith, and the Faith and Soules of others also, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2, 14. 18. the Metaphor is taken from Archers▪ who misse of their mark and ayme to signifie an errour in Faith, such as depriveth a man of the fruit which it brings forth, and of the end at which it aymes; which is no other then the salvation of their soules.</p>
            <p>We see hence, how <hi>needfull</hi> it is, that we all, but we especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <note place="margin">The needfulnesse <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> keeping t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine uncorrupt, by taking heed of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> causes of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it. Which are many.</note> of the Ministery, doe look well to our charge and to keep uncorrupt the Doctrine of God, that of Faith and love, and not to suffer it to be falsified or adulterated, but to beware of the causes of corrupting it, as <hi>negligence, suffering the enemy to sow Tares;</hi> want of <hi>Love</hi> to the Truth. This provokes God to take it from us, or to give us up to beleeve l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es. Its not said <note place="margin">Especially wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> love to it.</note> because they have not the truth, but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cause they have not the love of it, 2 <hi>Thess,</hi> 2. 10. 11. One o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her more speciall <hi>cause of corrupting the truth is,</hi> A yeelding too farre to others and their fash<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons for fear of offending them; which was <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>
               <note place="margin">Feare of offending the weak.</note> fault, who yet is blamed by <hi>Paul,</hi> and that justly, for not <hi>walking uprightly, according to the truth of the Gospel,</hi> Gal. 2. 1. 12. 13. 14. (and I wish i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were not our fault in forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to give the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, so long, through fear of offending them, who, too readily charge us with putting no difference between the holy or Saints, and prophane.) Yea an ascribing too much as to <hi>Places,</hi> suppose <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And an ascribin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> too much (as to</hi> Places, <hi>so) to</hi> Mens Persons▪</note> to <hi>Rome</hi> (which brought forth Antichrist:) to the bare <hi>Temple</hi> of the Lord which brought forth superstition in the Jews, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7. 4. So especially to mens <hi>Persons,</hi> whom we are ready to admire, and so in respect of their Persons, suck in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours; as doe such as ascribe so much to the Fathers by which means, <hi>Doctrine</hi> in Popery began to be corrupted, though, the Fathers themselves, would have all to examine their Writings by the Rule of the Scriptures. And so now a dayes, mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, or personall gifts are looked upon, and they admired, for their true or supposed learning, sanctity, or the like; and their errours, under such pretences, received without examination: Whereas, It is God onely that cannot lye; who must ever be
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:205727:28"/> acknowledged <hi>true and just in his sayings</hi> and word: and <hi>every</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 3. 4.</note>
               <hi>man altar;</hi> either actually, or in possibility, he may lie, and is not without perill of lying. Yea, <hi>God</hi> often in his Providence <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hy God often suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ers great men to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave</hi> great errors.</note> and Wisedom <hi>suffers great men to have great errours,</hi> and to be Authors of novel opinions in the Church, and to use their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to draw others from the truth to strange Doctrines, as to strange gods whom they have not known, not onely to humble <hi>them,</hi> if they belong to him, but <hi>to try us</hi> and our love to his <note place="margin">Especially to try their love to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd in truth.</note> truth, which he will have to be loved, and entertained for its own sake and worth.</p>
            <p>Which Mystery is taught us expressely by <hi>Moses,</hi> where speaking of some supposed great Prophets, who pretended dreams and revelutions yea science such as reaches farre above all humane knowledge, even ability to <hi>foretell future contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents,</hi> and to <hi>work wonders,</hi> (therein like unto God, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e properties these are, <hi>Esay</hi> 41. 23.) he tells us withall, that whereas the <hi>End</hi> of such Prophets is to draw people from God, and to goe after other gods, (or new and strange er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours) <hi>which they have not known;</hi> yet <hi>Gods end</hi> is thereby to <note place="margin">Deut. 13. 1. 2. 3.</note>
               <hi>prove them, to know whether they love the Lord their God with all their heart, and with all their soule.</hi> And therefore, saith the Lord, <hi>thou shalt not hearken to the Words of that Prophet.</hi> This is the <hi>Reason</hi> why God doth not forbid that to be taught, which yet he forbids to be heard or hearkned unto. And he gives the <hi>rule of triall</hi> withall, whilest he inserts these words, (speaking of those other Gods) <hi>Which thou hast not known,</hi> that is, which God never made <hi>known</hi> to them before. And <hi>vers.</hi> 4.<hi>—Ye shall walk after the Lord your God, and feare him—and that Prophet shall be put to death, &amp;c.</hi> So <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 19.</note>
               <hi>There must he Heresies among you, that they which are approved, may be made manifest among you.</hi> Such great and able <hi>Doctors,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome Instances gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ee</hi> Vincen. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inen. contra hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es, cap 15. 16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7. <hi>Where their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eresies also are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecited.</hi>
               </note> for Knowledge gifts, abilities and eloquence were <hi>Nestorius, Pho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inus,</hi> and <hi>Apoll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>naris,</hi> whose errours therefore were great <hi>Tentations.</hi> But what shall we say of some new upstart Teachers every way short of the fore named for <hi>Science,</hi> Parts and Learning; yet equalling▪ yea, farre surpassing them for hainousnesse of errour and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>asphemy? Shall we stumble at such blocks, and not look upon them rather as sent <hi>to try <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and our love to God, and his ancient truths? Avoyd them
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:205727:28"/> therefore; and keep we that <hi>Depositum,</hi> or that sound <note place="margin">Such to be avoyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>▪</note> Doctrine committed to our trust. Hold to that Forme or Patterne of <hi>wholesome words: If there come any unto you, and bring n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t this Doctrine,</hi> the Doctrine of Christ, <hi>receive him not into your house, neither bid him God speed</hi> John 2 Epist. ver. 9. 10. 11. And saith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi> and to us. <hi>Hold fast the faithfull Word as it hath been taught, &amp;c. for there are many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly and vain talkers and deceivers—whose mouthes must be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 9. 10.</note>
               <hi>stopped—</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>how</hi> this Doctrine is to be kept, many <hi>Directions</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Some moe</hi> Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>how and by what means this</hi> Depositum <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be kept.</hi>
               </note> might be given. <hi>First,</hi> The Apostle here, having given this Charge to <hi>Timothy,</hi> knowing it was not in his Power as of him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elfe to keep it; that is, either to fol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow these directions, or to avoyd the danger of sedu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ion▪ concludes with <hi>Prayer</hi> to God for him, saying <hi>Grace be with thee;</hi> and seales it by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. By Prayer for</hi> Grace.</note> adding his <hi>Amen.</hi> This sound Doctrine cannot be kept by our own strength: It hath many enemies, not onely Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and sedu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, but prophane persons, hypocrites, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors, our own corrupt nature &amp;c. Gods <hi>Grace</hi> must act him and us in this and all other like duties. <hi>Paul</hi> knew this in his own experience; what he could not effect (as he would) otherwise, he obtained by the <hi>Grace</hi> of Christ, which proved sufficient for him, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8. 9. By which grace and strength from Christ, he <hi>was able to doe and suffer all things.</hi> Phil. 4. 13. 2 Tim. 4. 17. We may work and act with God and his grace, not <hi>coordinately</hi> as causes in part with him, he halfe and we halfe; but <hi>subordinately</hi> and as we are In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struments, and are acted, directed ordered and assisted by his Grace. This made <hi>Paul</hi> say, <hi>By the Grace of God, I am what I am: and his Grace which was bestowed upon me, was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but I laboured more abundantly then they all; yet is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but the Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of God which was with me.</hi> 1 Cor. 15 10. I, and yet not I; how can that be? We may be said to labour, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t, hold fast, and keep, &amp;c. b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the will and understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is ours in which regard God gives and ascribes the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>▪ but the power and ability by which we doe these things is Gods, and is from hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Grace. All which <hi>teacheth us,</hi> as to Pray, indeavour, and seek strength and grace from
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:205727:29"/> Christ, and in all humility to depend in all things we doe, on his grace and assistance; so to acknowledge his goodnesse and mercy who Crowns his own work in us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Now as <hi>Paul beggs Grace</hi> for <hi>Timothy,</hi> so directing him elsewhere to the means of keeping this Charge, he sends him <note place="margin">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly Ghost <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>welling in us.</note> to <hi>the Holy Ghost,</hi> saying, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 14. <hi>That good thing which was committed un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o thee,</hi> (that is, <hi>the Forme of sound Words) keep, by the Holy Ghost, which dwelleth in us.</hi> For by the Holy Ghost, as it dwelleth in us, we are inabled hereunto. The holy Ghost is every where as a Spirit, but not as <hi>Holy;</hi> so onely it dwels in the hearts of the godly, as in its own <hi>house and temple,</hi> as having a <hi>propriety</hi> in us, and challenging <hi>Rule</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> works of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oly Ghost in help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to keep true</hi> Doctrine.</note>
               <hi>and Government over us,</hi> which it exerciseth, <hi>First,</hi> By capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vating our understandings, wills and affections and whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in us opposeth it selfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 5. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the heart at liberty. <hi>Thirdly▪</hi> By stirring up good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and affections in us, turning all the Powers of Soule and body to their right ends and ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ects: All which it doth <hi>voluntarily,</hi> at its own pleasure, not ours; and in such measure as it pleaseth, not alwayes putting forth it selfe to the full, either in mortifying of cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uption, or aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arding strength. And therefore we are to writ on the motions of it, yea. (in the case we have now in hand) <hi>to stirre up the gift of God</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 1. 6.</note>
               <hi>which is in us,</hi> and the graces of his Spirit, by which we may be further strengthened and inabled; and that made easie to us and sweet, which otherwise is harsh and hard▪ It is the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ust be waited on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccording to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord.</note> Spirit of God by which the Word and true Doctrine of Christ was, and is given, as it <hi>inlightneth:</hi> and it is the s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Spirit of God which by the <hi>truth, sanctifieth us,</hi> and which by the <hi>Power</hi> of it and according to the <hi>Rule</hi> of the Word, will keep and preserve us in the truth, and discover unto us all Spirits of errour, contrary to the Word, which seducers and Hereticks are ready to father on the holy Ghost, (which Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists pretend to be President in their Councells, as others in their Factious Assemblies) though they follow not the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Word.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Lastly,</hi> So rest on, and trust to the Spirits direction and assistance, as to be sure, and most carefull, constantly to <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our care to hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ancient truth.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:205727:29"/>
               <hi>and hold to the old Apostolicall and Fundamentall truths</hi> of the Word, which were at first made known by the Spirit, which is ever like it selfe, It is the Spirit that is promised to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach us all <hi>things;</hi> the things there spoken of are such things as Christ spake unto hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Disciples, being yet present with them, of which they were not so capable at that time. Now, saith Christ, <hi>the holy Ghost, whom the Father will send in my</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 14. 25. 26. <hi>And especially to remember them.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Name, he shall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatsoever I have said unto you.</hi> Now what was brought to their remembrance, the Apostles taught, and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>For which we have directions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>se given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, by</hi> Peter▪</note> sought to bring to the remembrance of other Disciples; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Peter, I will not be negligent to put you alwayes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of these things, &amp;c.</hi> 2. Pet. 1. 12 and accordingly <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy, If thou put the Brethren in remembrance of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Paul.</note>
               <hi>these things, thou shalt be a good Minister of Jesus Christ, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed up in the words of Faith, and of good Doctrine, whereunto thou hast attained: but refuse prophane and old Wives Fables, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 6. 7. and 11. <hi>These things command and teach—</hi>And what saith the Apostle <hi>John? Let that abide in you, which</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <hi>ye have heard from the beginning—if so—ye shall continue in the So<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e and in the Father—These things have I Written un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you concerning them that seduce you,</hi> 1 John 2. 24. 26. And <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe saith to us, as once to the <hi>Iews. If ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>And</hi> Christ <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe. comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nding this care in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>in my Word, then are ye my Disciples indeed: And ye shall know the truth,</hi> John 8. 31. 32. And it was the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which Christ gave to the Church of <hi>Pergamos—thou hast holden fast my Name, and hast not denied my Faith,</hi> that is, the Doctrine of Faith <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. 13. And his <hi>Exhortation</hi> and <note place="margin">Reproving the want of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> warning to the Church in <hi>Sardis, Remember therefore how thou hast received and heard, and hold fast, and repent,</hi> Revel. 3. 3. So Tit 1. 9.<hi>—A Bishop must be one—holding fast the faithfull Word▪ as he hath been taught.</hi> And to <hi>Timothy,</hi> saith <hi>Paul▪ Hold fast the Forme of sound Words, which thou hast heard of me, in faith and love which is in Christ Iesus,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13. And to the <hi>Colossians,</hi> whom he sends to Christs ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse in the mystery of God and his Word, <hi>Lest any should beguile them with entising Words,</hi> he adds this Exhortation. <hi>As ye have therefore received Christ Iesus the Lord, so walke ye in</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:205727:30"/>
               <hi>him, rooted and built up in him, and established in the Faith, as ye have been taught, abounding therein with thanksgiving: beware least any may spoile you through Philosophy and vata de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, &amp;c.</hi> Coloss. 2. ver. 3. 4.—6▪ 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Still we see we are sent to the <hi>Doctrine and faith once,</hi> (and but once) <hi>delivered to the Saints,</hi> both for our rooting and building up in it, for which, if we could also be but <hi>true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thankefull,</hi> we should not so easi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y be beguiled with entising words, or given up to vain-deceit.</p>
            <p>I <hi>Conclude</hi> first, with that serious advice given by <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Conclusion, Or▪ The Authors <hi>Farewell</hi> to his Hearers, Read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, if not, to the VVorld: being an Indeavour to have Apostolicall Truths remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Pet. 2 19. 20.-26.</note>
               <hi>Now I beseech you Brethren, marke them which cause divisions and offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have Learned, and avoyd them,</hi> Rom. 16. 17. And with that of <hi>Peter,</hi> which was his Farewell, (as this is like to be mine) to his Charge, (the <hi>converted</hi> Jews, but now in great part, after his first Epistle to them, <hi>perverted</hi> by errours; having also <hi>turned the grace of God into wantonnesse, and forsaken the truth.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>—I will endeavour, that you may be able after my decease, to have these things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Especially,</hi> Peters Vide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>et.</note>
               <hi>in Remembrance,</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 15.</p>
            <p>But <hi>what things?</hi> First, <hi>Negativrly,</hi> not first, cunningly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised <hi>Fables, vers</hi> 16. Secondly, Not new or other lights <note place="margin">Not Fables, or yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w and forme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y unheard of disco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>veries.</note> and discove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies to be revealed in after Ages, and not former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or yet <hi>then</hi> heard of; whether <hi>Popish</hi> unwritten verities as mysticall reserves; or any other New Gospel, other O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, unheard of Truths as some perhaps would gath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r from <hi>Peters</hi> mentioning of the <hi>present truth,</hi> ver. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h as they think, relates to or inferres, <hi>future truths</hi> not then made known. Clearer manifestations of the same ancient truthes we deny not▪ and here we are to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of things, not to he new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>discovered,</hi> but <hi>remembred,</hi> such and no other then our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>t, of which he saith▪ These <hi>things</hi> (all needfull t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings) <hi>have I spok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n unto you, being yet present with you:</hi> There things <hi>then</hi> were present truths <hi>Iohn.</hi> 14. 25. yet he tells <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that he will send his holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> who shall teach th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>all things,</hi> and bring, saith he, <hi>all things to your remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:205727:30"/>
               <hi>whatsoever I have said unto you,</hi> vers. 26. Not any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ew or other Truths, which yet so many now would father <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on the Spirit. This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>Faith which was once</hi> (and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t once) <hi>delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude 3. to be now, and yet contended for, against all new and other supposed truths or revelations.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Affirmatively;</hi> These <hi>thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in <hi>Peter,</hi> were Apostoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Truths, which he had taught them in his former Epistle, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. But in the</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Grace <hi>of God</hi>
               </note> and now teacheth them in this, he had written and testified <hi>that this</hi> (id est. <hi>the Word, which by the Gospel was Preached unto them,</hi> 1 Peter 1. 25) <hi>is the true Grace of God, wherein</hi> (saith he) <hi>ye stand,</hi> 1 Peter 5. 12. <hi>ed est,</hi> the <hi>true</hi> Doctrine <note place="margin">Not abuse<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Or yet extended beyond its bounds.</note> of free grace not grace misapplied or abused to wantonnesse and licenciousnesse, not <hi>racked or extended</hi> beyond its bounds. Which grace if it were still truely taught, we should not heare of such Doctrines as these, First, <hi>Iustification, before</hi>
               <note place="margin">As it is by many.</note>
               <hi>Vocation and Faith.</hi> Secondly, <hi>God seeth no sinne in Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Shewed in si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Particulars.</note> Thirdly, They sinning, though grossely, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as much in Gods favour and love, as the glorified Saints: yea, and they, even before renued repentance, are bound to beleeve it. Fourthly, <hi>No reconciliation of God to</hi> sinners, but onely of sinners to God. Fifthly, Reconciliation to God, without <hi>satisfaction</hi> by Christ. Nay sixthly, <hi>Ʋniversall gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e;</hi> yea <hi>actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all red<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mption in time, and salvation</hi> of all, even of very Devils &amp;c. Here is grace enough, and free enough, if it were <hi>true</hi> Grace.</p>
            <p>He again in this Epistle teacheth and exhorts to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Piety</hi> and tells us, that God hath called us <hi>(through the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi>
               <note place="margin"> 2. <hi>The</hi> Doctrines o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>true Piety.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>of him)</hi> to <hi>glory</hi> (as the end) and to <hi>vertue</hi> (as the means;) <hi>to life and godlinesse,</hi> See 2 Peter 1. 3. 4. 5. 6. and 8. 9. 10.<hi>—If ye doe these things, ye shall never fall.</hi> And in the body of the Epistle intending to arme them and us against <note place="margin"> 3. <hi>The</hi> Doctrine <hi>Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> understood,</hi>
               </note> seducers and false teachers, 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 2. 1. 2. &amp;c. he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends unto them the <hi>holy Scriptures,</hi> both Old and New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stament right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y understood. See 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 1 19. 20. 21. and <note place="margin">Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h Nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Testam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 2 <hi>Peter</hi> 3. 2. These he makes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the filed pole and compasse which he would have them and us to steere our course by.</p>
            <p>This being so, we see what to judge of our prophane <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cripturists,</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:205727:31"/> who deny the divine authority of Scriptures▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> generall. And of such whether <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>▪ who deny the authority of the <hi>Old Testament</hi> so that being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> therewith▪ (as in point of the Magistrates Power in reform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion, and punishing seducers, and of their usage an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> practises according to Gods command and, Institution o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Sacraments, and things belonging to the Covenant of <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>light</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> grace in those times,) We are put off with this, Oh, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was in the times of the Old Testament, Things are more spirituall now▪ &amp;c. Yea, they so look upon the Writings thereof, as if they were onely and meerly a dead Let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, without-life, spirit, ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, without Christ, as if men were f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> onely with temporall prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ses, of an earthly <hi>Canaan,</hi> &amp; c▪ which indeed to avow. I can account little: other th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. But no marvaile, seeing now, in these dayes of the Gospel, some will be learned above the Scriptures <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en of the New Testament too, yea, will be above all <hi>Ordinance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>▪</hi> if not above <hi>Christ</hi> himselfe, pretending a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Communion with God, and more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>med are then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>I might also shew, what Things both for Doctrine and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> onely <hi>Peter▪</hi> but <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> &amp;c. would haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, hold fast, and teach to others. <hi>See</hi> 2 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 15. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 2. 3. 4. <hi>So</hi> Titus 2. 12. 13. 14. 15. <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things speak and exhort. So</hi> Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s 3. 1.—8. and Philip. 4. 8. 9▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Thess. 4. 1. 2. 3—<hi>So</hi> Iohn, 1 Iohn 1. 4. and chap. 2. 1.—3.—6.—24.—26. These <hi>things have I Written unto you, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> that seduce you.</hi> And <hi>chap▪</hi> 5. 13. But to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude. The Knowledge and Remembrance of such thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would keepers from errour, and from <hi>falling from our own s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>esse.</hi> 2. Peter 3. 17. And so should the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> transmitted pure to Posterity, when we are dead and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>▪</p>
            <trailer>FINIS▪</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>